<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Gopi Notes</title>
  <subtitle>Notes on .NET &amp; Sitecore</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-10T17:20:09.916Z</updated>
  <id>http://gopigujjula.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Gopikrishna Gujjula</name>
    <email>gopikreddy.gn@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template/</id>
    <published>2016-12-10T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-10T17:20:09.916Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of <a href="/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/">Saturday Sitecore Learning series</a>, till now we looked into,</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-CMS/">What is CMS?</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-About-Sitecore/">What is Sitecore?</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/">Sitecore installation</a> (I prefer using SIM)</li>
<li><a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/">Setting up Visual Studio Solution</a> (Outside webroot)</li>
<li><a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/">About Sitecore Databases</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/">Exploring Default home page</a></li>
</ul>
<p>By this time, I assume that you have both Sitecore and Visual Studio project setups in your machine, If not take your time and setup both.<br>From now onwards let’s look into each core Sitecore concepts in a more detail manner.</p>
<p>In this post let’s look into one of the important part of Sitecore content, which is Template.</p>
<h4 id="Templates"><a href="#Templates" class="headerlink" title="Templates"></a>Templates</h4><p>Templates, also commonly referred to as <strong>Data Templates</strong>, which are basic building blocks of any content in Sitecore. Every piece of content (page or components) in Sitecore needs a data template to define what it is.</p>
<p>To understand it better, Templates can be compared to Class (In object oriented programming) definitions,</p>
<ul>
<li>Each Class contain fields with their respective data types, similarly every Template contain fields, with their respective field types. (Ex: <em>Single-line text</em>)</li>
<li>Any number of instances can be created for a class, similarly we can create any number of content items for a single template.</li>
<li>Class supports inheritance, similarly templates also supports inheritance, in which a single template can inherit from multiple base templates, to inherit the common fields.</li>
</ul>
<p>Before creating any content, first we need to create a Template with fields and their types. In a nutshell, They specify the data fields and many other settings that can be applied to content upon creation.</p>
<p>All Templates are defined under /sitecore/templates in Sitecore tree structure.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/templates-tree.png" alt=""></p>
<p>To open templates, we can open them either from Content Editor, or from Template Navigator, which is present in Start menu. (Start menu is available in Desktop mode)</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-manager.png" alt=""></p>
<p>While exploring <a href="/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/">default home page</a>, we noticed that home page content item, is using Sample item template, which can be found in <em>/sitecore/templates/Sample/Sample Item</em><br><img src="/css/images/default-home-template.png" alt=""></p>
<p>There are various templates types,</p>
<ul>
<li>Page Templates</li>
<li>Datasource Templates</li>
<li>Folder Templates</li>
<li>Branch Templates</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Page Templates:</strong><br>As the name suggests these are the templates, used to create page content. Similar to other template types, this also can contain fields, field sections, and inheritance. But only page templates can have presentation settings, Sitecore uses these presentation settings to render the page. All the components are added in presentation settings.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Datasource Templates:</strong><br>Component items are created using this templates. Same component item can be re-used on multiple pages using datasource. This templates do not contain any presentation settings.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Folder Templates:</strong><br>These templates are used for folders; mainly they enable reuse of a folder’s set of insert options to maintain which items can be created in the folder.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Branch Templates:</strong><br>Normally we create a single item from one template. But what if we need to create a set of certain content items, whenever we create particular item. This can be done manually, but it is time consuming and error prone. Branch templates are useful in this scenarios. With branch templates, we can specify a predefined hierarchy of dependencies<br>that are created each time an item is created from the template.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Next post we will look into Sitecore field types.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;As part of &lt;a href=&quot;/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/&quot;&gt;Saturday Sitecore Learning series&lt;/a&gt;, till now we looked into,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Default Home Page</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/</id>
    <published>2016-12-03T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-03T13:00:53.228Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I explained on how to install Sitecore and setup new project in my previous posts, Now it’s time to drill down on the Sitecore default home page. Let’s explore it’s Template, Layout, sub-layout, Content Item etc. At last we will see how the Content Author can change the text using Content editor.</p>
<p>Before we move further, few of you may not be convenient with terminology (template, layout, sub-layout) but no issues just follow the steps, we will discuss more about each topic in coming posts.</p>
<p>If we load the newly installed Sitecore website, we can see the below page, as the website home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-default-homepage.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now let’s look into each and every aspect from Sitecore side, first let’s login into Sitecore using <strong>admin/b</strong> credentials,</p>
<p>From Launch pad, navigate to Content Editor, by directly clicking on the <strong>Content Editor</strong> option, or through <strong>Desktop</strong> option, it is a good practice to go from Desktop, as we can open multiple windows, and navigate among them, similar to windows desktop, and also having start menu. This is not possible by directly selecting Content Editor option from Launch pad.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-desktop.png" alt=""></p>
<p>If you click on Desktop mode, select Sitecore logo/start button and select “Content Editor” option.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/start-menu.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In Content Editor, navigate to the Home content item (<strong>/sitecore/content/Home</strong>),</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/default-home-content.png" alt=""></p>
<h4 id="Data_Template_3A"><a href="#Data_Template_3A" class="headerlink" title="Data Template:"></a>Data Template:</h4><p>In Sitecore, every content item is created from Template. Template contains field definition, and presentation information. Some say <em>“Templates are like class definitions. Content is like an instance of that class.”</em><br>In Sitecore tree, all the templates are present under <strong>sitecore/Templates</strong></p>
<p>For the default “Home” page Template is already present in Templates section. We can see the Template name, In Quick Info section, which is <strong>Sample Item</strong> in this case. By clicking on the template name, we can navigate to the template item.(if you opened in Desktop mode, Template will be opened in new window, else on the same window) or we can navigate to the template using its path <strong>/sitecore/templates/Sample/Sample Item</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-structure.png" alt=""></p>
<p>By looking into <strong>Sample Item</strong> Template’s <strong>Builder</strong> tab, we can understand that there are two fields defined in it, which are <strong>Title</strong> (text Type) and <strong>Text</strong> (Rich Text Type). <strong>Field Type</strong> determines the control to manage the content by content author using the editing interface.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-fields.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Standard Values</strong> for a particular template, lists all the fields including inherited fields. All the presentation details are assigned on Standard values.<br>For all the page templates, we have a presentation, where we can assign a layout and components (sub-layouts). On request of a web page, Sitecore assembles the page dynamically from it’s content and the presentation components.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-presentation.png" alt=""></p>
<h4 id="Presentation_3A"><a href="#Presentation_3A" class="headerlink" title="Presentation:"></a>Presentation:</h4><p>Now let’s look into presentation components, both layout, and sub layouts. All the layouts, sub layouts, renderings (in MVC), will be present under <strong>sitecore/Layout</strong> in the Sitecore tree.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layoust.png" alt=""></p>
<p>From <strong>Sample Item</strong> template presentation, we can see that there is one layout <strong>(Sample Layout)</strong>, and three components <strong>(Sample Sublayout, Sample Inner Sublayout,</strong> and <strong>Sample Rendering)</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/presentation.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Let’s explore Sample Layout first, which is present in <strong>sitecore/Layout/Layouts/</strong> path. Layout is kind of master page in ASP.NET terminology, where we have basic html tags are added, and placeholders are defined. On Click of Sample Layout item, we can see the <strong>Path</strong> field, there is a .aspx page path is given, which contains all the HTML code with respect to the page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/main-layout.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layout-path.png" alt=""></p>
<p>If we observe the layout code, we can see that HTML tags are present and also a placeholder with key as <strong>main</strong> is added. This is the placeholder where, other page components are going to be embedded.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layout-code.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Similar way if we look at <strong>Sample Sublayout</strong> item, which is under <strong>/sitecore/Layout/Sublayouts</strong>. This is an .ascx file.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sublayout.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sublayout-code.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Similar to this component, other page components also have code files with respect to them.<br>ASP.NET webforms -&gt; <strong>.ascx</strong> files<br>ASP.NET MVC -&gt; <strong>Controller</strong> rendering, or <strong>View</strong> rendering.<br>XSLT -&gt; XSL Rendering</p>
<p>If we look at the Sample rendering which is a xsl rendering, this is where we are rendering both the fields, <strong>‘title’ &amp; ‘text’</strong>, which are created in template.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/xslrendering.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/xslrenderingcode.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now let’s get back to our home item, where we have already content present for both the fields, which we can see on home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/conten-output.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Till now we have seen Templates, Standard values, presentation, layout, sub-layout and renderings. Stay tune to this space for my next posts to discuss more detail on each item we used in home page.</p>
<h4 id="Hello_World"><a href="#Hello_World" class="headerlink" title="Hello World"></a>Hello World</h4><p>We will try changing the Title field content to <strong>Hello World</strong>, and verify that text is changing on home page or not. After making any change, we need to publish the item; As I discussed earlier our changes will save in to Master database. On Click of publish latest modifications/final content gets pushed to <strong>web</strong> database. Refer Below screenshot for final output we are expecting. Hello world is indeed appearing on home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/helloworld-content.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Sitecore supports both ASP.NET web forms and MVC, but default home page comes with all web forms related code. Currently most of new Sitecore implementations are done in MVC. So in coming up posts, we will always try to see the code examples in MVC.<br>ASP.NET web forms is still very much in picture, because lot of implementations till now are done in web forms. Whenever we are maintaining those applications, web forms knowledge is very much required.<br>That’s all for this week.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;As I explained on how to install Sitecore and setup new project in my previous posts, Now it’s time to drill down on the Sitecore default
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Code review check list</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Basic-Code-Review-Checklist/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Basic-Code-Review-Checklist/</id>
    <published>2016-11-26T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-29T05:08:36.071Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I am going away from our series, and sharing the presentation on the Sitecore basic code review check list. This presentation deck is part of the knowledge share session, I had delivered in office.</p>
<p>This check list helps Sitecore developers to better enhance the Content Author experience in managing their content.</p>

	<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/xBecChQ8JHkFDL" style="width:100%;height:550px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen> </iframe> <div style="margin-bottom:5px">


</div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;This week, I am going away from our series, and sharing the presentation on the Sitecore basic code review check list. This presentation 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Presentation" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Presentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Databases</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/</id>
    <published>2016-11-19T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-29T04:54:11.671Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By this time, we have Sitecore website running in our machine, and also ready with Visual Studio solution setup. From now, we will look into Sitecore concepts, in both theory and hands on as well.<br>As we all know Sitecore is a database driven CMS, in this post let’s look into Sitecore databases.</p>
<h4 id="Sitecore_Databases_3A"><a href="#Sitecore_Databases_3A" class="headerlink" title="Sitecore Databases:"></a>Sitecore Databases:</h4><p>From developer’s perspective, until and unless any customization is required, we don’t directly deal with databases, we always access data using Sitecore Api’s. but it is very important to know about, what are all databases Sitecore uses.</p>
<p>Sitecore uses multiple databases to manage both content and also analytics related data.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-databases.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Content_Databases"><a href="#Content_Databases" class="headerlink" title="Content Databases"></a>Content Databases</h5><p>Sitecore uses three databases to maintain content. It always supports MS SQL server, but in Sitecore latest version 8.2 also supports <a href="https://kb.sitecore.net/articles/087164" target="_blank" rel="external">Oracle 12g</a>. But Oracle is only supported in <strong>CMS only mode, not for xDB</strong>.<br><img src="/css/images/oracle.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Sitecore CMS uses the following three databases,</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Core:</strong> This database contains all settings related to Sitecore, ex: Sitecore User Interface (Content Editor, Experience Editor, etc.) configuration. Using this database, we can add any new application, or shortcut on Sitecore launch pad or desktop.<br>This database also contains information about authentication and authorization, (Users &amp; roles)</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Master:</strong> This is content authoring database. All content authors mainly interact with this database, using either Content Editor or Experience Editor. It contains all versions of any content or assets.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Web:</strong> This is also called live database. It contains all the live content, which is serving on the production website. When content author modifies any content, and publish it, content copied over to web database. Master database contains all versions of content, whereas web database only contains live version of content. Web database is subset of the Master database.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When we log into Sitecore, by default it always displays content from Master database, but we can select the database to show the content from other databases, like as shown below,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/database-selection.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Collection_Database__28Mongo_DB_29_3A"><a href="#Collection_Database__28Mongo_DB_29_3A" class="headerlink" title="Collection Database (Mongo DB):"></a>Collection Database (Mongo DB):</h5><p>As stated in Sitecore documentation, “In the Siteecore Experience Database (xDB), the <strong>Collection database</strong> is the central repository for storing contact, interaction, history &amp; automation data.”<br>It uses <strong>MongoDB</strong> - a highly scalable document-based NoSQL database solution.<br>Prior to Sitecore Version 7.5, all of analytics data used to get stored in <strong>Analytics</strong> database which was part of MS SQL server.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>tracking.live:</strong><br>The tracking.live database is used by two entities:</p>
<ol>
<li>Task Storage (defined in <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.config</em> file)</li>
<li>Live Processing Pool (defined in <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file)<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2508/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p><strong>tracking.history:</strong><br>The tracking.history database is used by only one entity:<br>History Processing Pool (defined in the <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file).<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2512/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>tracking.contact:</strong><br>The tracking.contact database is used by only one entity:<br>Contact Processing Pool (defined in the <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file).<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2525/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="Reporting_Database_3A"><a href="#Reporting_Database_3A" class="headerlink" title="Reporting Database:"></a>Reporting Database:</h5><p>The reporting database is a SQL Server database that stores aggregated data from the collection database suitable for fast querying and reporting. This database contains aggregated data from collection DB.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;By this time, we have Sitecore website running in our machine, and also ready with Visual Studio solution setup. From now, we will look i
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Visual Studio - Project - Outside Web root</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/</id>
    <published>2016-11-12T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-23T06:16:35.470Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent post we had seen, how to set up project inside the web root. But this option is only useful for POC’s. Most of the time outside web root option is more useful. In this post let’s explore more advanced,</p>
<p>I am using <strong>Visual Studio 2015 community/professional</strong> edition, and <strong>Sitecore 8.2</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Outside web root setup steps:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Open the Visual Studio, and navigate to <strong>File -&gt; New -&gt; Project</strong>, to create new project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Select the <strong>.NET Framework</strong> (in our case 4.5.2) version, and select the <strong>ASP.NET web application</strong> template.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enter the <strong>Name</strong> of the project, specify the <strong>Location</strong> field, and then click on OK to continue.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now we get another dialog, to select the project template. Here select <strong>Empty</strong> template present under <strong>ASP.NET 4.5.2 Templates</strong> section, and check the MVC checkbox as shown below, and click OK to proceed.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once the project is created, solution contains the files as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-solution-explorer.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now from the project, remove <strong>Web.config</strong>, and <strong>Global.asax</strong> files, otherwise while publishing, these files will override the respective Sitecore files.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-file-delete.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once after deleted, we need to copy both <strong>Web.config</strong> and <strong>Global.asax</strong> from web root into the project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-file-paste.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Create a folder with name <strong>App_Config</strong>, then copy the <strong>ConnectionStrings.config</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.config</strong> files from web root to the project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-config files.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-config files-copy.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Next step is to add Sitecore references. We need both <strong>Sitecore.Kernel.dll</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.MVC.dll</strong>, Let’s grab these files from web root. Create a directory in Project file system, let’s call that <strong>Assemblies</strong>, and copy the two dll’s to inside the directory.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-copy-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-copy-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-reference.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Please double check on the Mvc version compatibility <a href="https://kb.sitecore.net/articles/087164" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>, and make sure you are using correct .NET Mvc version. We can verify the MVC version in <strong>Web.config</strong> file as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-mvc-version.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now our project is all set. To deploy we need to create a publishing profile. Select <strong>Publishing Method</strong> as <strong>File System</strong> and specify the local Sitecore instance web root path.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-3.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>At last, click on the <strong>Publish</strong> button, we can see the Site is published to web root folder.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-4.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>To confirm the publish to web root folder, we can navigate to bin folder in web root folder, and see that <strong>SIMSitecore.dll</strong> is copied over.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-verification.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now try to load the site, and check whether we are able to login to Sitecore or not.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-deploy-verify-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-deploy-verify-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p>That’s all, thanks for reading.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;In recent post we had seen, how to set up project inside the web root. But this option is only useful for POC’s. Most of the time outside
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Visual Studio - Project - Inside Web root</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Inside-webroot/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Inside-webroot/</id>
    <published>2016-11-05T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-03T13:09:40.138Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post we will look into creating Visual Studio project for the installed Sitecore.</p>
<p>There are mainly two approaches to create the project,</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Inside the web root</strong><br>Here both deployed files, and solution files in same location. Setting up is pretty straight forward, and good for small POC’s, but not recommended for real time projects.</li>
<li><strong>Outside the web root</strong><br>This is the most preferred one, as it separates the Sitecore, and our code and Sitecore in different locations, and easy to version Control. This is the <em>recommended</em> approach from core Sitecore team.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this post we will look into the first approach, I am using <strong>Visual Studio 2015</strong> edition.</p>
<p><strong>Inside the web root Setup steps:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Open the Visual Studio, and navigate to <strong>File -&gt; New -&gt; Project</strong>, to create new project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Select the <strong>.NET Framework</strong> (in our case 4.5.2) version, and select the <strong>ASP.NET web application</strong> template.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enter the <strong>Name</strong> of the project, and in <strong>Location</strong> field specify the newly installed Sitecore web root path (in our case <em>F:\inetpub\wwwroot\SIMSitecore\Website</em>), and make sure to uncheck the <strong>Create directory for solution</strong> checkbox, and then click on OK button.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project-name.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now we get another dialog, to select the project template. Here select <strong>Empty</strong> template present under <strong>ASP.NET 4.5.2 Templates</strong> section, and check the MVC checkbox as shown below, and click OK to proceed.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once the project is created, solution contains the files/folders as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-solution-explorer.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>If we go to the web root, we can observe there is a new folder created with the specified project name, and also new solution file (.sln) with the same name.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Drill down the newly created folder (SIMSitecore), to see the files, which are same as shown in the VS solution explorer.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/project-drilldown.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Close the VS solution. Copy the Properties directory, SIMSitecore.csproj, and SIMSitecore.csproj.user files to the main web root directory.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-files.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now delete the <strong><em>SIMSitecore subdirectory</em></strong>, which is present inside the Website directory.</li>
<li>Open the SIMSitecore.csproj file in Visual studio, and delete all the missing files from project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-remove-files.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Add references to <strong>Sitecore.Kernel.dll</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.MVC.dll</strong> files which are in Website-&gt;bin directory.<br><img src="/css/images/VS-sitecore-kernerl.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Navigate to the Sitecore references</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>To be continued -having some trouble to setup</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;In this post we will look into creating Visual Studio project for the installed Sitecore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mainly two approaches to creat
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Launchpad</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Launchpad/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Launchpad/</id>
    <published>2016-10-29T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By this time, we have latest version (8.2) of Sitecore running in local. It’s ok to install using either of the three approaches, web application installer, or manual installation, or using SIM.</p>
<p>Before going ahead to create .NET web application, it’s good to have a look at Sitecore launch pad, different components, and the content tree structure.</p>
<p>For any application, to open Sitecore, we need to append <strong><em>/sitecore</em></strong> to the URL. In my case, URL is <a href="http://testsitecore/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://testsitecore/</a>, so to open Sitecore click on <a href="http://testsitecore/sitecore" target="_blank" rel="external">http://testsitecore/sitecore</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-login.png" alt=""></p>
<p>To login to Sitecore, default Administrator credentials are as below<br><strong><em>username: admin<br>password: b</em></strong></p>
<p>Once we login, we can see the Sitecore Launchpad,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-latest-launchpad.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In the Launchpad, we can see there are 4 sections,</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong><em>Marketing Applications:</em></strong> This section contains, all the components relate to Digital Marketing suite. These are the main components using which marketers can connect better with customers.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Content Editing:</em></strong> This section is the main heart of the CMS. Using these components, Content Authors can add, edit, or delete the content.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Control Panel:</em></strong> As the name suggests, using these components, we can do the administrative activities, like Search indexing manager, clean up databases, and localization.. etc.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Access Management:</em></strong> This section contains all the user, role, and security related components.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Now we look into some of the main components,</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Content Editor:</em></strong> This is where Content Authors manage content. They can either add, edit, or delete the content. As a <em>developer</em>, we frequently access this to create templates, rendering, and placeholders etc. In this all items are displayed in tree structure.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-content-editor.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Experience Editor:</em></strong> Here Content Authors can create/modify the content in the live mode. In previous Sitecore versions this was called Page Editor.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-experience-editor.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Experience Analytics:</em></strong> This section contains more of reports, like Channel groups by visits, Top campaigns by value, Top goals by conversions, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-experience-analytics.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In the next post, we will look into how to create a .NET web project for Sitecore.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;By this time, we have latest version (8.2) of Sitecore running in local. It’s ok to install using either of the three approaches, web app
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Installation with SIM tool</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/</id>
    <published>2016-10-22T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:24:41.196Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: Sitecore with SIM"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: Sitecore with SIM</h3><p>Last week, we had seen how to install Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM) tool. This week we will explore how to install Sitecore using SIM.</p>
<p>Among all the three (<strong>Web Application Installer, Manual Installation, and SIM</strong>) available options, to choose, SIM is the most preferred choice among all the Sitecore developers. The Main reason for that is the flexibility it provides in managing the Sitecore sites.</p>
<p>Let’s dive into step by step Sitecore installation,</p>
<p><strong>Step 1:</strong><br>If we remember in the last post, while installing SIM, we configured <em>4 settings</em>, these are very crucial while installing Sitecore. Before proceeding any further, we need to double check on these settings, and if it is required, make any necessary changes.</p>
<ul>
<li>Instance Root Folder</li>
<li>SQL Server Connection String</li>
<li>Sitecore License File</li>
<li>Local repository (Make sure to place downloaded Sitecore zip folder inside this path)</li>
</ul>
<p>To verify the 4 options, open the Home tab, and click on the Settings</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-home.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 2:</strong><br>For additional settings, click on Advanced Settings. But before making any changes, please go through the <a href="https://github.com/sitecore/sitecore-instance-manager/wiki/Advanced" target="_blank" rel="external">documentation</a> very carefully.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-advanced-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 3:</strong><br>Click on the Install Instance<br><img src="/css/images/SIM-install-instance.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-install-new-instance.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 4:</strong><br>Make all the necessary changes, Site Name, and Host name. Location value is prepopulated from the settings <em>Instance Root Folder</em>. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-new-sitecore.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 5:</strong><br>Some more options for instance details. Better to keep the default values, until and unless you are fully aware of the modifications. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-instance-details.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 6:</strong><br>If any of the Sitecore modules are present in the <em>Instance Root Folder</em>, those all are going to be listed here. We can select the modules, to install with Sitecore. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-module-list.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 7:</strong><br>You can select any available custom packages, and click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-custom-packages.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 8:</strong><br>Select any Configuration presets, and click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-configuration-presets.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 9:</strong><br>Finally all the selected modules, and custom packages, will be listed for review. Make any final modification and click on <em>Install</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-instance-review.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 10:</strong><br>Now Sitecore is getting installed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-sitecore-installation.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 11:</strong><br>Once the installation is completed, you can check the listed options, and click on <em>Finish</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-sitecore-installation-finish.png" alt=""></p>
<p>See you on next <strong><em>Saturday</em></strong>.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM) </title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-SIM-Installation/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-SIM-Installation/</id>
    <published>2016-10-15T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.433Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: SIM tool Installation"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: SIM tool Installation</h3><p>Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM), is the tool, using which we can install, maintain, and uninstall the Sitecore. Among Sitecore developers, this is the most preferred choice to maintain Sitecore installations.</p>
<p>SIM provides rich set of choices, you can watch this wonderful <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqYhjoW83RE" target="_blank" rel="external">video</a>, in which <a href="https://twitter.com/vasiliyfomichev" target="_blank" rel="external">Vasiliy Fomichev</a> explains the main features.</p>
<p>In this post, we will look into SIM installation, in the next we will look into Sitecore installation using SIM.</p>
<p>Installation Steps</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Download SIM tool from [Sitecore Marketplace] (<a href="https://marketplace.sitecore.net/en/Modules/Sitecore_Instance_Manager.aspx" target="_blank" rel="external">https://marketplace.sitecore.net/en/Modules/Sitecore_Instance_Manager.aspx</a>).<br><img src="/css/images/SIM1.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on the <strong>Link</strong> to get the ClickOnce version of SIM.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM2.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>It will be redirected to <a href="http://dl.sitecore.net/updater/sim/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://dl.sitecore.net/updater/sim/</a>. From here click on <strong>Install and Launch</strong>.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM3.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on the downloaded <strong>SIM.Tool.application</strong><br><img src="/css/images/SIM4.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>On the Initial Configuration Wizard, click on Next to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM5.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on Next to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM6.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>In the previous post, we had downloaded latest Sitecore Zip (<strong>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729</strong>) file. For local repository point to the location of Sitecore folder, and point the local path for Sitecore License file.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM7.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Here give a SQL connection string, with <strong>(Data Source, User ID and Password)</strong> values.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM8.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Specify the File system path, and make sure to give the Network Service access, by clicking on the <strong>Grant</strong> button.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM9.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM10.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM11.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>After the successful installation, SIM will check for any sitecore websites in the specified File System path. In my local I already have TestSitecore website, the same is listed below.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM12.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation&quot; class=&quot;headerlin
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Manual Installation</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Manual-Installation/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Manual-Installation/</id>
    <published>2016-10-08T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.408Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: Manual Installation: Installing from the .ZIP File"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: Manual Installation: Installing from the .ZIP File</h3><p>In this post, we will look into Manual installation option.</p>
<p><strong><em>Installation Overview:</em></strong><br>Before proceeding, we need to understand what will happen in the installation process. In my previous post we discussed about installation using executable(.exe). There after giving all the information, and click on the install button, in the background it will perform the below operations,</p>
<ul>
<li>Creates 5 databases, like shown below,<br><img src="/css/images/sitecoredb.png" alt=""></li>
<li>Copies Sitecore site in the specified destination folder path.</li>
<li>Creates new website in IIS, and point to the destination folder.</li>
<li>Takes care of the other details like updating the database information in <em>ConnectionStrings.config</em> file, folder securities, and other configurations.</li>
</ul>
<p>When we go through manual installation, we need to take care of all the above steps.</p>
<p><strong><em>Sitecore Manual Installation:</em></strong><br>I have downloaded latest Sitecore .ZIP file (<em>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729</em>) from <a href="https://dev.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">dev.sitecore.net</a>. Unzip the file, then we can see the three folders as shown below, copy all these three folders to destination folder.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-folders.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now we will look into Database setup,</p>
<p><strong>Step 1</strong>: Open SQL Server Management Studio (SSMS) in Admin mode, Right click on Databases, and select Attach new databases. All the .mdf and .ldf files are present inside the Databases folder, which can be found in the unzipped folder. Attach all five databases.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/attach-db.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 2</strong>: Next step is to create new user. Navigate to Security –&gt;Login, and click on ‘New Login’, and map all the five databases, <em>with db_owner role</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/db-login.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1a.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1b.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1c.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now all the databases are set.</p>
<p>Next we will proceed to Website setup:</p>
<p><strong>Step 1</strong>: Copy your Sitecore license (<em>license.xml</em>) file under Data folder, and update the path in <em>Website\App_Config\Sitecore.config</em> file.<br><figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&#60;sc.variable name=&#34;dataFolder&#34; value=&#34;F:\inetpub\wwwroot\Data&#34; /&#62;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p>
<p><strong>Step 2</strong>: Update the <em>ConnectionStrings.config</em> file, which is present in <em>Website\App_Config</em> path.<br><img src="/css/images/connectionstring.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 3:</strong> Open IIS, and create new website, and make sure to add new host with site name.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/IIS-website.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now run the site, it will load the Sitecore default home page.<br>In next post we will explore the Sitecore installation option using SIM.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_I
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Installation : Web Application Installer</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Web-Application-Installer/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Web-Application-Installer/</id>
    <published>2016-10-01T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-12-10T08:24:45.813Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My Apologies. Due to some unavoidable reasons, I couldn’t add any posts in the last two months.</em></p>
<p>Again I am re-initiating it from this month. In learning series, till now we have seen what is Sitecore, resources, and certification information. From now onwards, we will look into Initial Setup, installation, and implementation parts.</p>
<p>Sitecore installation can be done in three ways</p>
<ol>
<li>Sitecore web application installer</li>
<li>Sitecore Zip (manual installation)</li>
<li>Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM)</li>
</ol>
<p>Sitecore installation consists of mainly three steps.</p>
<ol>
<li>DB Setup</li>
<li>Web site Deploy location</li>
<li>IIS configuration for site</li>
</ol>
<p>In this post, we will look into first option.</p>
<p><strong><em>Sitecore web application installer:</em></strong><br>Among all the three options, web application installer is the easiest one, as it is through exe. We just need to run .exe file and follow the instructions.</p>
<p>Before installing Sitecore, we need to have following installed, with administrator access</p>
<ul>
<li>.NET framework 4.5 and above (for Sitecore 8.2)</li>
<li>IIS</li>
<li>Visual Studio - Community/Professional/Enterprise</li>
<li>MS SQL Server or Oracle</li>
<li>Mongo DB</li>
</ul>
<p>You can find more details <a href="https://kb.sitecore.net/articles/087164" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a> about Sitecore compatibility.</p>
<p>Download latest Sitecore exe file -version (<em>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729</em>) from <a href="https://dev.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">dev.sitecore.net</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Installation Steps</strong><br><strong>Step 1:</strong> Unzip the downloaded file, and run the <strong>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729.exe</strong> file, and click on Next -&gt;.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 2:</strong> Accept the license agreement, and click on Next -&gt;.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 3:</strong> Select the type of installation. Here we have three options,<br>   <em>Complete:</em> both Sitecore web site and database.<br>   <em>Database Only:</em> It is useful when we already have web site setup, but need fresh DB.<br>   <em>Client Only:</em> It is useful if we are using the database from any other common server with in the organization.<br>If you are trying to install in personal mission then choose Complete option otherwise based on requirement choose the option and click on Next -&gt;.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-3.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 4:</strong> Give a unique name for this new instance and click on Next -&gt;.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-4.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 5:</strong> Select the Sitecore license file. I do not have much information on how to get the license file. I am using my firm (Sitecore Platinum Partner) license file. I guess for individual developer, there is a Student trail license which is valid for one month.<br>Once license file is selected, it will auto populate the below details. Then click on Next -&gt;.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-5.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 6:</strong> Both SQL Server and Oracle are supported. Select the database vendor from dropdown, give the Database server name, and credentials. On click of Advanced settings, we can change Database Prefix, which will be defaulted to previously given Sitecore instance name. <em>Imp Note: Login Id should have admin access enabled in DB server.</em><br>Click on OK to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-6a.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-6b.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 7:</strong> Select the IIS root path/wwwroot folder location for Sitecore installation. From Advanced settings, can also select locations for Data, and Database. Click on Next -&gt; to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-7a.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-7b.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 8:</strong> Give web site name, and click on Next -&gt; to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-8.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 9:</strong> At last one more time review all the options, and click <strong>Install</strong>.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-9.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 10:</strong> Sitecore will take some time to get installed, and after finishing the installation, select the Launch Sitecore check box, and click on Finish.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-10a.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-10b.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 11:</strong> Now, you can see Sitecore home page in your default browser. You can login with default Sitecore credentials,<br><strong>User name: admin<br>Password: b</strong></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-installation-11.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Cheers on successful installation.In my next post I will explain about Manual Installation.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Apologies. Due to some unavoidable reasons, I couldn’t add any posts in the last two months.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again I am re-initiating 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My Journey from Hotel Management student to Software Engineer</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/07/My-Journey-from-Hotel-Management-student-to-Software-Engineer/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/07/My-Journey-from-Hotel-Management-student-to-Software-Engineer/</id>
    <published>2016-07-03T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-17T19:49:54.634Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/css/images/medium.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Every journey has to start some where, I am going to start mine from my graduation.</p>
<p>Why am I telling this now? As, I am celebrating my 6th year (1st July) work anniversary, want to go back to where i had started. Currently I am working as a Senior Engineer in an IT firm at Bangalore.</p>
<p>I am a hotel management graduate(also a chemistry graduate), then went on to do a masters in computer science and later became a software engineer.</p>
<p>Please read the full post <a href="https://goo.gl/rR0Ijv" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/medium.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every journey has to start some where, I am going to start mine from my graduation.&lt;/p&gt;

    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Career" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Career/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning : Developer Resources</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/07/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Developer-Resources/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/07/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Developer-Resources/</id>
    <published>2016-07-02T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-19T16:09:44.410Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-launchpad.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now we explore what are all the resources available for developers to learn Sitecore.</p>
<p><strong>Prerequisite</strong> : As we know that, it is built on .NET platform, so we should have basic understanding, and little hands-on experience in .NET, ASP.NET (Web Forms or MVC), C#, and little bit in SQL server or RDBMS concepts.</p>
<p>Sitecore company is providing two options to train backend developers, although course curriculum is similar in both,</p>
<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://www.sitecore.net/services-and-support/training/classroom-training/back-end-developers" target="_blank" rel="external">Classroom Training</a>:<br><strong>Duration</strong>: 4 days<br><strong>Fees</strong>: varies country to country, but approximately around USD $2000+.<br><strong>Lectures by</strong>: Sitecore Certified Trainers<br><strong>Hands on lab</strong>: Yes<br><strong>Certification</strong>: I do not have much information on this.<br><strong>Sitecore License</strong>: Not sure about this.<br><strong>More details</strong>: <a href="http://www.sitecore.net/en/services-and-support/training/classroom-training/back-end-developers/wnd8-sitecore-website-development-for-net-developers" target="_blank" rel="external">Check here</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://elearning.sitecore.net/public/searchResults.aspx?q=&amp;ty=ML.BASE.DV.SearchAnyWords" target="_blank" rel="external">eLearning</a><br><strong>Duration</strong>: 14 hours<br><strong>Fees</strong>: USD $1500.<br><strong>Lectures by</strong>: Pre recorded videos by Trainers<br><strong>Hands on lab</strong>: Yes<br><strong>Certification</strong>: The purchase of this course includes a Sitecore Certification Exam Voucher (for single attempt).<br><strong>Sitecore License</strong>: Sitecore license is must to practice labs. Independent developers may apply for a one month Temporary Student License.<br><strong>Course Access</strong>: Up to 4 months.<br><strong>More details</strong>: <a href="https://elearning.sitecore.net/public/ContentDetails.aspx?id=ADA90A1B1DDD4CAF848234763A00135B" target="_blank" rel="external">Check here</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>I have taken eLearning course, which was fully sponsored by my company <a href="http://www.verndale.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Verndale</a>. Course is having very good explanation of the concepts, and after the course completion, passed the Certification exam, and got the <strong><em>Sitecore 8 Professional Developer Certification</em></strong>.</p>
<p>One main drawback of the course is, it is based on ASP .NET Web Forms. But mostly all new projects are into ASP.NET MVC implementation. But anyway Sitecore concepts are more of similar in both.</p>
<p><strong>Other options</strong><br>If you are unable to spend that much amount on course, and if your company is not sponsoring it, then it is little bit difficult to kick start. But there are so many wonderful people who share their knowledge through blog posts, webinars, and videos.<br>There is a very good community around Sitecore, with lot of MVPs and certified developers.</p>
<p><strong>Developer Portal</strong>: <a href="https://dev.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">dev.sitecore.net</a><br><strong>Community documentation</strong>: <a href="http://sitecore-community.github.io/docs/" target="_blank" rel="external">sitecore-community.github.io/docs/</a><br><strong>Slack Channel</strong>: <a href="https://sitecorechat.slack.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">sitecorechat</a><br><strong>Unofficial Sitecore 8 Training Webinar Series</strong>: <a href="http://www.akshaysura.com/2016/02/03/unofficial-sitecore-8-training-webinar-series-full-curriculum/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.akshaysura.com/2016/02/03/unofficial-sitecore-8-training-webinar-series-full-curriculum/</a><br><strong>Stack Exchange</strong>: <a href="https://sitecore.stackexchange.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">sitecore.stackexchange.com</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/sitecore-launchpad.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we explore what are all the resources available for developers to learn 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - About Sitecore</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-About-Sitecore/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-About-Sitecore/</id>
    <published>2016-06-25T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.534Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore_logo.png" alt=""></p>
<p>After learning about <strong>WCM</strong> platforms, now I am trying to understand more about <strong>Sitecore</strong> as a technology and as well as product, and it’s market position.<br>As a developer, it is very much crucial to know that, when we choose it as a career path/option, and to make sure we are investing our time on technologies which are having bright future.</p>
<p>After going through several websites and posts, here is my notes,</p>
<p>For seven years in a row, the <strong>Sitecore Experience Platform</strong> has been placed in the Leaders quadrant of <strong>Gartner’s Magic Quadrant for Web Content Management</strong>.</p>
<p>In ranking Sitecore as a leader In CMS, <strong>Gartner</strong> cited the company’s strengths as:</p>
<p><em>Sitecore has an industry-leading, compelling and executable vision for a “contextual delivery machine.” The Sitecore Experience Database (xDB), which promises to deliver the long-sought-after “360-degree view of the customer,” contributes to this vision.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore</a> is one of the leading enterprise-level Content Management System in .NET world, using which we can create both Intranet portals and enterprise web sites.</p>
<p>It supports <strong>ASP.NET MVC</strong> and as well as <strong>Web Forms</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore company</strong> was started in Copenhagen in <strong>2001</strong> by five friends who saw a need for a better way to build and manage websites.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore product</strong> was mainly introduced as WCM platform, which combines the components dynamically on to page and deliver to the user. Later on it has evolved to fully digital marketing platform, and now it is called as <strong>Sitecore Experience Platform</strong>, which included Web Content Management, Customer Intelligence, and Cross-Channel Delivery.</p>
<p>Sitecore is mainly trying to achieve, “<strong>To deliver the right content to the right person at the right time and on the right device.</strong>“</p>
<p>Below pic depicts, what exactly Sitecore Experience Platform provides,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecorexp.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Please check this <a href="http://www.sitecore.net/en/products/sitecore-experience-platform" target="_blank" rel="external">link</a> to know more about the experience platform.</p>
<p><em>“Sitecore is a high-performance, scalable, extensible ASP.NET web CMS that generates all output<br>dynamically and uses the same components and system architecture for both content and application<br>pages.”</em> – <strong><a href="https://community.sitecore.net/technical_blogs/b/sitecorejohn_blog?tag=f1b992e4-4511-44a9-aa1a-7b48e5225d9a" target="_blank" rel="external">John West</a> (All time Sitecore MVP)</strong></p>
<p>Current version of <strong>Sitecore is 8.2</strong>, which is going to be released on August - 2016.</p>
<p>Sitecore continuously and very rapidly evolves as a product, to provide more options and features to the customers. It provides a variety of licensing option to clients.</p>
<p>Sitecore code is not open source.</p>
<p>There is a very good article <a href="http://www.cygnet-infotech.com/blog/8-reasons-why-many-enterprise-cmos-choose-sitecore" target="_blank" rel="external">8 Reasons Why Many Enterprise CMOs Choose Sitecore</a></p>
<p>Credits:<br><a href="http://www.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore</a><br><a href="http://blogs.perficient.com/microsoft/2016/10/sitecore-named-a-leader-in-gartner-magic-quadrant-for-wcm/" target="_blank" rel="external">Perficient</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/sitecore_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning about &lt;strong&gt;WCM&lt;/strong&gt; platforms, now I am trying to understan
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Content Management System</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-CMS/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-CMS/</id>
    <published>2016-06-18T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.515Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/css/images/cms.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In this post we mainly discuss about what is CMS (Content Management System) or sometimes called WCMS.</p>
<p>When I think of any tool or technology, first thing that comes to my mind is, under which category it falls into, and what are the benefits of using it. for example, when we say C#, what is it? C# is a programming Language, same as c, or C++. (I am not getting into the details of OOP language or functional language), when we say Entity Framework or Hibernate, these are Object Relational Mapping tools, and MS SQL Server is RDBMS, similar way Sitecore is one of the enterprise-level <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system#Web_content_management_system" target="_blank" rel="external">Content Management System (CMS)</a> platform.</p>
<p>So what exactly CMS means?<br>I found one of the definitions in <a href="https://www.lynda.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Lynda</a> site, which I feel very apt,</p>
<p><strong>“Server-side software that is designed to simplify the creation and maintenance of sites. These systems manage online content, generate web pages, and allow users to upload and change content without requiring technical expertise”</strong> – Lynda.com</p>
<p>For normal websites, if client needs to add or modify any content (page, text, image or video), they cannot make this changes directly, first they need to reach out to technical team (Web Developer), with their help they can make the required changes. But this is time consuming process, and definitely not feasible for the rapidly content changing site.</p>
<p>In this cases, clients need a way to update their content as quickly as possible. Content Management Systems help client in this process. CMS provides a way to streamline the content addition, approval, and publishing. CMS provides an easy UI to create or modify the content.</p>
<p>There are lot of Content Management Systems for each technology (PHP,.NET, and Java etc).</p>
<p>Some of the popular CMS among all technologies,</p>
<ol>
<li>Wordpress</li>
<li>Joomla</li>
<li>Drupal</li>
</ol>
<p>Popular CMS in .NET,</p>
<ol>
<li>DotNetNuke</li>
<li>Sitecore</li>
<li>Umbraco</li>
<li>EpiServer</li>
<li>Kentico</li>
<li>Sitefinity</li>
<li>mojoPortal</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Credits :</strong> <a href="http://forerunner.com.au/digital-media/content-management-systems/" target="_blank" rel="external">Image Courtesy</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/cms.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we mainly discuss about what is CMS (Content Management System) or sometimes c
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Career Awards</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/career-awards/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/career-awards/</id>
    <published>2016-06-12T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-17T20:07:16.126Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2015 - Spot Award at 𝐍𝐓𝐓𝐃𝐚𝐭𝐚,<br>2016 - VET Award at 𝐕𝐞𝐫𝐧𝐝𝐚𝐥𝐞…</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/nttdata.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/verndale.jpg" alt=""></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;2015 - Spot Award at 𝐍𝐓𝐓𝐃𝐚𝐭𝐚,&lt;br&gt;2016 - VET Award at 𝐕𝐞𝐫𝐧𝐝𝐚𝐥𝐞…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/nttdata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Career" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Career/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Introduction</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Series/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Series/</id>
    <published>2016-06-11T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T12:26:00.473Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore_logo.png" alt=""></p>
<p>It has been since few months, I had started learning Sitecore. In Sitecore, there are lot of concepts to learn, &amp; practice, and I have come across some wonderful videos, articles, and blogs, which explains the concepts very nicely. As I was learning, wanted to take notes, so that it will aid me in better understanding the concepts. The same notes I want to share it here.<br>One of the video series I love on Sitecore is <a href="https://goo.gl/Jud1E9" target="_blank" rel="external">Weekly Friday video series covering Sitecore Best Practices</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/VasiliyFomichev" target="_blank" rel="external">Vasiliy Fomichev</a> a Sitecore MVP.<br>I like his idea of one video on every Friday. With his inspiration, I have named this series as Saturday Sitecore Learning. Here every Saturday I will be posting one article on my learning. It will be kind of notes.</p>
<p>Before started learning Sitecore, I have more than 5 years of experience in Web development, mainly using ASP.NET web forms and MVC, but never heard of neither CMS platform nor Sitecore term.</p>
<p>At last why Sitecore? This is the easy one to answer, because in the organization where I work, we develop mostly digital marketing solutions, and we use Sitecore more.</p>
<p>In the next post, let’s see what exactly is CMS platform, and why do we need one?</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/css/images/sitecore_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been since few months, I had started learning Sitecore. In Sitecore, there
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>ASafaWeb - Automated Security Analyzer for ASP.NET Websites</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/05/asp-net-security-analyser/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/05/asp-net-security-analyser/</id>
    <published>2016-05-21T17:14:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T11:55:13.660Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="ASafaWeb"><a href="#ASafaWeb" class="headerlink" title="ASafaWeb"></a><a href="https://asafaweb.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">ASafaWeb</a></h3><p>Recently I am trying to improve my knowledge on both general security and web security concepts. I was going through technical articles, blogs, and pluralsight courses. Also started attending the monthly <a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Bangalore#tab=Next_Meeting" target="_blank" rel="external">OWASP tech meetup</a>, where they mainly discuss on the security concepts and related technologies.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/asafeweb.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In <a href="http://pluralsight.com" target="_blank" rel="external">Pluralsight</a>, there are lot of security courses authored by <a href="http://app.pluralsight.com/author/troy-hunt" target="_blank" rel="external">Troy Hunt</a>, where he clearly explains the concepts in a simple manner. Even in his <a href="https://www.troyhunt.com" target="_blank" rel="external">blog</a>, there are wonderful articles. I learned a lot from his courses and articles.</p>
<p>This <a href="https://asafaweb.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">ASafaWeb</a>, is the tool developed by Troy Hunt, for specifically analyzing the ASP.NET websites for any security risks. This tool can analyze the vulnerabilities of the hosted site, and also it doesn’t require any access to the code. It mainly send some extra HTTP requests to the given site URL, and give us the report by analyzing the responses.</p>
<p>The security check is mainly done for the following,</p>
<ol>
<li>Tracing</li>
<li>Custom Errors</li>
<li>Stack Trace</li>
<li>Request Validation</li>
<li>HTTP to HTTPS redirect</li>
<li>Hash DoS patch</li>
<li>ELMAH log</li>
<li>Excessive Headers</li>
<li>HTTP only cookies</li>
<li>Secure cookies</li>
<li>Clickjacking</li>
<li>View state MAC</li>
</ol>
<p>ASafaWeb only checks for the common configuration related vulnerabilities, but there are many other security related aspects, like SQL injection, Cross Site Scripting, and Cross-Site Request Forgery, etc..</p>
<p>So for what are we waiting, just go to <a href="https://asafaweb.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">ASafaWeb</a>, and enter your ASP.NET website URL, and click on Scan to get the report. We can also Schedule the scans, but we need to register for that. Currently it is in Beta stage.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/asafeweb-1.png" alt=""></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;ASafaWeb&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ASafaWeb&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;ASafaWeb&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asafaweb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ASP.NET" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/ASP-NET/"/>
    
    
      <category term="ASP.NET" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/ASP-NET/"/>
    
      <category term="Security" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Security/"/>
    
      <category term="Tools" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Tools/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>ASP.NET Core day - BDotnet</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/05/aspnetcoreday/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/05/aspnetcoreday/</id>
    <published>2016-05-09T10:37:28.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-05T11:59:13.928Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another month, another <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/BDotNet/" target="_blank" rel="external">BDotent</a> community event, but this time it is on latest <strong>ASP.NET Core</strong> technology and a full day event.</p>
<p>We are not going to miss it. :)</p>
<p>For me all the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/BDotNet/" target="_blank" rel="external">BDotent</a> events are about getting to know the gist of the topic and leave with enough enthusiasm to explore the remaining details.</p>
<p>One more big thing is Networking, It is always pleasure to meet and know the fellow developers and to share the information on what type of applications we work on, and what all the tools &amp; technologies we are using.<br><em>(This time met some of the old buddies, and also made some new friends.)</em></p>
<p><strong>Overall, it’s mainly the experience of being present at the event.</strong></p>
<p>As usual, all the speakers are wonderful in sharing their knowledge, and their enthusiasm conveys us the most. All the topics are very well chosen, like connecting the dots to get the overall picture on the ASP.NET core.</p>
<p>Thank you for all the awesome speakers, and the organizing committee.</p>
<p>It was wonderful to witness the house packed sessions.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/aspnetcoreday.png" alt=""></p>
<p>My key takeaways from the event are,</p>
<ol>
<li><p>As there is an another new framework is out, we shouldn’t jump in and start using it for all kind of applications. We first need to understand our application use cases, then evaluate the options to take the decision.</p>
</li>
<li><p>ASP.NET (Web forms) framework is not going any where. It is very much supported. New features will still be coming out for this. There are lot of application, which are running on ASP.NET framework. (I had a big doubt on the ASP.NET web forms support, glad that it is clarified.)</p>
</li>
<li><p>ASP.NET Web forms is not supported in ASP.NET core. It is   very much dependent on System.Web.</p>
</li>
<li><p>POCO controller are very much useful when we do not require all the features from BaseController.</p>
</li>
<li><p>In new framework, Dependency Injection is already integrated, But if require, we can very much plug in any of the third party DI containers.</p>
</li>
<li><p>New web server (Kestrel - cross platform) written from the scratch, for the .NET core.</p>
</li>
<li><p>RC2 is going to be out in mid May, and RTM is going to be released by June end.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Cloud born applications.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Tag helpers, more cleanness, more readability.</p>
</li>
<li><p>ASP.NET core more of modularized, empty project means it’s clearly empty. Whatever we want, we need to add it.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><em><strong>Volunteer</strong> : It was my pleasure to help the event in a very small way (being part of the registration process). Thanks <a href="https://www.facebook.com/LohithGN" target="_blank" rel="external">Lohith</a> for the opportunity.</em></p>
<p>some pics,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/aspnetcoreday-1.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/aspnetcoreday-2.png" alt=""></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Another month, another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/BDotNet/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;BDotent&lt;/a&gt; community event, but
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ASP.NET" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/ASP-NET/"/>
    
    
      <category term="ASP.NET" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/ASP-NET/"/>
    
      <category term="Bangalore Tech event" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Bangalore-Tech-event/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Agent Ransack - Free File Searching Utility</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/04/Agent-Ransact-tool/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/04/Agent-Ransact-tool/</id>
    <published>2016-04-30T10:37:28.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-05-13T06:56:43.591Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Agent_Ransack"><a href="#Agent_Ransack" class="headerlink" title="Agent Ransack"></a>Agent Ransack</h3><p>Everybody knows about, how painful to search for files in Windows, and also there is no easy way to search the content of all the files with particular text.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/agent-ransack.png" alt=""></p>
<p><a href="https://www.mythicsoft.com/agentransack" target="_blank" rel="external">Agent Ransack</a> comes to our rescue, this is a very powerful file searching tool, which provides us lot of options to search the content, and generate reports.</p>
<p>We can also search the remote server contents from our local, this is the most useful feature for me, which helps &amp; saves me lot of time.</p>
<p>There are lot of options, like searching with regular expressions, date modified range, and match case etc. We can export the results to Tabular, CSV, or text formats.</p>
<p>There is also a licensed version with more features <a href="https://www.mythicsoft.com/filelocatorpro" target="_blank" rel="external">File Locator Pro</a>.</p>
<p>We have also some other search utilities like <a href="http://www.voidtools.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Everything</a>, and <a href="http://mfctips.com/2014/01/16/everything-vs-agent-ransack-vs-searchmyfiles-vs-file-finder/" target="_blank" rel="external">SearchMyFiles</a>, but among all Agent Ransack stand out.</p>
<p>There is a very nice <a href="http://mfctips.com/2014/01/16/everything-vs-agent-ransack-vs-searchmyfiles-vs-file-finder/" target="_blank" rel="external">article</a> which explains the details about different search utilities.</p>
<p><strong>Credits : Thanks to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/peterfranceschini" target="_blank" rel="external">Peter Franceschini</a>, for letting me know about this wonderful tool.</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Agent_Ransack&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Agent_Ransack&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Agent Ransack&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Agent Ransack&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everybody knows about, how
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Tools" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Tools/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
