<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Gopi Notes</title>
  <subtitle>Notes on .NET &amp; Sitecore</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:06.741Z</updated>
  <id>http://gopigujjula.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Gopikrishna Gujjula</name>
    <email>gopikreddy.gn@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sitecore Enhancing Content Author Experience - Part 2 (Layouts)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience-Part-2/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience-Part-2/</id>
    <published>2017-02-26T04:54:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:06.741Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Layouts_level"><a href="#Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Layouts_level" class="headerlink" title="Enhancing Content Author Experience - Layouts level"></a>Enhancing Content Author Experience - Layouts level</h4><p>This is the second post as part of <a href="/tags/Content-Author-Experience/">Sitecore Enhancing Content Author Experience series</a>.</p>
<p>In last post, we had explored how can we enhance content author experience from template perspective, in this post, let’s explore at layouts level.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-layouts-content-author-experience.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="1-_Datasource_Location"><a href="#1-_Datasource_Location" class="headerlink" title="1. Datasource Location"></a>1. Datasource Location</h5><p>In Sitecore, each page is a collection of components. We can add any number of components to a page, and some of the components we add to the page, have their own associated content. Content authors can select the associated  content using data source. If we are not restricting data source location, then full content tree is shown in the selectable items list, then content authors have a tough time to navigate and select the associated content.</p>
<p>Datasource location helps us in this situation, we can set selectable items location, while creating sub-layout/rendering using <strong>Datasource Location</strong> field.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/datasource-selection.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong><em>without data source location (full content tree is listed)</em></strong></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/without-datasource-location.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong><em>with data source location (items shown, based on the location)</em></strong></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/with-datasource-location.png" alt=""></p>
<p><a href="http://firebreaksice.com/sitecore-rendering-datasource-locations/" target="_blank" rel="external">Here</a> you can read more information about data source location.</p>
<h5 id="2-_Datasource_Template"><a href="#2-_Datasource_Template" class="headerlink" title="2. Datasource Template"></a>2. Datasource Template</h5><p>Once we specify data source location, still content author has to know, which is the associated content item to choose. If there are only similar content items present in the location, then it becomes easier. But what if there are different variety of content items are present, then it is our job to guide them, to select proper items.</p>
<p>We can achieve this by using Datasource template, which can be set on sub-layout/rendering <strong>Datasource Template</strong> field.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/datasource-template-selection.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Without Data source Template:</p>
<ul>
<li>Any content item can be selected.</li>
<li><strong><em>Create New Content</em></strong> option is grayed out, because, Sitecore does not know, using which template it has to create new item. (I remember in Sitecore certification exam, there was a question on when does Create New Content is grayed out)</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/without-datasource-template.png" alt=""></p>
<p>With Data source template:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sitecore prompts with a message, when other template item is selected.</li>
<li>Create New Item option is available, using which Content authors can create new content directly from here.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/with-datasource-template.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="3-_Placeholder_Settings"><a href="#3-_Placeholder_Settings" class="headerlink" title="3. Placeholder Settings"></a>3. Placeholder Settings</h5><p>We can empower the Experience Editor using placeholder settings (Allowed Controls). It is very important to set allowed controls for each placeholder, other wise it would be difficult for content authors to know, which all the components can be placed on particular placeholder.</p>
<p>Without allowed controls being set, content authors have to navigate and find the component to add.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/placeholder-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong><em>Without Allowed controls being set</em></strong></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/without-placeholder-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong><em>With Allowed controls being set</em></strong></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/with-placeholder-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="4-_Thumbnail"><a href="#4-_Thumbnail" class="headerlink" title="4. Thumbnail"></a>4. Thumbnail</h5><p>After allowed controls is being set, now content authors can see the list of renderings in <strong>Select a Rendering</strong> window. But wouldn’t be good to provide a visual clue, about what design they see on page, by selecting a particular component. Thumbnail is useful for this purpose.</p>
<p>Thumbnail can be set at Rendering/sub-layout items. We have an option to take screen shot as well, or can select an image from media library.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/rendering-thumbnail.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Below, we can observe that Article module is having thumbnail set, but Product module is not having any thumbnail.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/with-rendering-thumbnail.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Thank you for reading, in next post, will explore the tips from content level.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Coding :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Layouts_level&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Layouts_level&quot; class=&quot;headerlin
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Layouts" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Layouts/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Content Author Experience" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Content-Author-Experience/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sitecore Enhancing Content Author Experience - Part 1 (Templates)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience-Part-1/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience-Part-1/</id>
    <published>2017-02-25T21:05:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:04:34.893Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Template_level"><a href="#Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Template_level" class="headerlink" title="Enhancing Content Author Experience - Template level"></a>Enhancing Content Author Experience - Template level</h4><p>This is the first post as part of <a href="/tags/Content-Author-Experience/">Sitecore Enhancing Content Author Experience series</a>.</p>
<p>As a Sitecore developer, I always feel we have two primary users of our work; One is a website visitor, and second one is Content authors. Most of the time, we tend to give more importance to our site visitor, as they make the business happen, but we need to give equal importance to Content authors, to improve their overall experience of managing content.</p>
<p>In this three post series, let’s explore some of the tips to enhance content author experience, in Template, Layout, and Content levels. As part of the this post, let’s look into templates.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-templates-content-author-experience.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="1-_Template_Icon"><a href="#1-_Template_Icon" class="headerlink" title="1. Template Icon"></a>1. Template Icon</h5><p>Template Icons help to visually separate semantically related content items. We can Visually provide clues to the type of item in the content tree, by choosing unique icon to each template.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/contenttree.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Image Courtesy: <a href="https://sitecorecreative.wordpress.com/2012/07/13/sitecore-icon-selector/" target="_blank" rel="external">https://sitecorecreative.wordpress.com/2012/07/13/sitecore-icon-selector/</a></p>
<p>As a content author, how do you feel, when you see the left side and right side content trees in above screen shot. Definitely left side tree, is much more helpful, because by seeing the icons, we can understand what type of item it is.</p>
<p>Icons can be set at template level, or item level. Two ways we can set icons, one is by directly clicking on the template icon, another one is from configure tab.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-icon.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-icon-configure.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="2-_Field_Type"><a href="#2-_Field_Type" class="headerlink" title="2. Field Type"></a>2. Field Type</h5><p>Selecting appropriate field type is key for managing the content, as field type effects, what control content author use to modify that field content. Sitecore provides lot of in-build field types, and if we needed we can also create custom field types. Read here to know more about <a href="/tags/Sitecore-Field-Types/">field types</a>.</p>
<p>For example, let’s take the case of Multlist or Multlist with search field types. Both provides a list of items, to choose, but second field type provides extra search option too, this is very much useful, when there are lot of selectable items, other wise it is difficult to scroll and select.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/list-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/list-with-search-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="3-_Field_Source"><a href="#3-_Field_Source" class="headerlink" title="3. Field Source"></a>3. Field Source</h5><p>For list field types, we can control the list of selectable items to be displayed, using field source property. Field source can be set using; Sitecore query, path, and GUID. When Treelist field type is used, and source is not set, full Sitecore tree is displayed in selectable items. Then it is very difficult for Content author, to navigate and select the appropriate item.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/without-field-source.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/with-field-source.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="4-_Field_Help_Message"><a href="#4-_Field_Help_Message" class="headerlink" title="4. Field Help Message"></a>4. Field Help Message</h5><p>Help message gives extra information to Content Authors about particular field. Sitecore provides the ability to add help information to fields in three ways – using short description, long description, and help link. This three fields are part of the standard fields.<br>Short description is displayed beside the field title, Long description is visible on field title mouse over, Help link can be navigated, by clicking on field title.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/help-message.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="5-_Field_Sorting"><a href="#5-_Field_Sorting" class="headerlink" title="5. Field Sorting"></a>5. Field Sorting</h5><p>For each page, or component, there may be lot of content fields to manage. But among all the fields, there may be few fields which gets changed very frequently. But if these fields are at bottom of the field list, every time content author has to scroll, to make any updates. It is better to place most frequently modified fields on top, using Sort order field, which is part of the standard fields. By default Sitecore will set sort order to 100 points.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/field-sort-order.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="6-_Folder_Templates_-_Insert_Options"><a href="#6-_Folder_Templates_-_Insert_Options" class="headerlink" title="6. Folder Templates - Insert Options"></a>6. Folder Templates - Insert Options</h5><p>Folder templates are used for the purpose of organizing a collection of items. (ex: Rendering folder, Template Folder). The <strong>insert options</strong> configuration provides that the templates relevant to the folder are immediately available.<br>The default folder template for content items is <strong>/sitecore/templates/Common/Folder</strong>.<br>To create a custom folder template, we need to inherit from the default folder template, and then configure with custom insert options.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/folder-template.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="7-_Parameter_Templates"><a href="#7-_Parameter_Templates" class="headerlink" title="7. Parameter Templates"></a>7. Parameter Templates</h5><p>There is a different between <strong>What</strong> &amp; <strong>How to</strong> content. What content means is the actual content on site, whereas How to content means, content which controls behavior of the content, example, Search page size, CSS class, number of carousel items.<br>Most of the time, we tend to mix <strong><em>How to</em></strong> content fields with <strong><em>What</em></strong> content fields, but it is very important to not to mix both, to make our content more cleaner.<br>On component level, we can manage “How to” content using key value pair section. But Content Authors may find difficult to remember, &amp; enter exact key names, to avoid this we can use parameter templates.</p>
<p>Managing <strong>How to</strong> content becomes lot easier using parameter templates. We can create parameter templates, like any other templates, but these templates should inherit from <strong><em>/sitecore/templates/System/Layout/Rendering Parameters/Standard Rendering Parameters</em></strong></p>
<p>Once parameter template is created, it can be added to component using <strong>Parameters Template</strong> on the rendering.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/parameter-template.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Only one parameter template is allowed on one component, that is the reason inheritance is very important for the parameter templates.</p>
<p>Once parameter template is added to component, Content can be modified from Control Properties which can be accessed using Page item Presentation details.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/parameter-template-content.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Thank you for reading, in next post, will explore the tips from layout level.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Coding :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Template_level&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Enhancing_Content_Author_Experience_-_Template_level&quot; class=&quot;headerl
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Content Author Experience" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Content-Author-Experience/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates Part 5 (Template Inheritance)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-5/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-5/</id>
    <published>2017-02-25T05:47:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:07.023Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Template_Inheritance"><a href="#Template_Inheritance" class="headerlink" title="Template Inheritance"></a>Template Inheritance</h4><p>This is the fifth post as part of <a href="/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/">Sitecore Template series</a>.</p>
<p>In last three posts, we discussed about <a href="/tags/Sitecore-Field-Types/">field types</a>, now let’s explore what is template Inheritance, and the benefits it provide.</p>
<p>Template is a collection of fields, where fields can be defined on a template, or can be inherited from other templates. Similar to Object Oriented Programming, where a class can be inherited from another class, in Sitecore, a template can be inherited from another template.</p>
<p>Each template can inherit fields, field sections, standard values, and potentially other properties from any number of other templates.</p>
<p>Sitecore uses lot of template inheritance, for system templates. There is a <strong>Standard Template</strong>, which defines field sections, and fields common to all items.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-template-inheritance.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Whenever we create any new template, it will always inherit from the <strong>Standard Template</strong>, and all the <strong>System Fields</strong> comes with it.</p>
<p><strong>Why do we use Inheritance?</strong><br>In general, we use Inheritance, for <strong>reusability</strong>. Where we can define the properties, &amp; methods in one common place, and access it from all other places. for <strong>Maintainability</strong>, where it is easy to make modification at single location.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore Template Inheritance Benefits</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Reusability: We define common fields in one template, and inherit in all other templates. This avoids duplication.</li>
<li>Maintainability: Modify the fields in the main template, all the templates automatically gets the modifications.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Scenario:</strong><br>Let’s take a Scenario, where we have Article template, and Podcast template, both are having certain fields common, like <strong><em>Title, Date, and Description</em></strong> etc. What if we create a new base template, with all these common fields, and inherit this new base template, in both Article and Podcast template. In that way we remove the duplication, and increase the reusability.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-template-inheritance-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-template-inheritance-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Important points</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If you directly or indirectly inherit from the same template more than once, Sitecore behaves as if you had inherited that template only once.<br>For example, Template B inherits from Template A, Template C inherits from both Template A &amp; B, here indirectly we are inheriting Template A (once directly, and another indirectly from B), multiple times. But Sitecore inherits Template A only once.</li>
<li>One template, can only inherit one set of presentation details. If a template inherits from two templates, and both have presentation details, only the first template’s presentation details in the inheritance list will be used. (In the coming post, we will explore more about presentation details)</li>
<li>If two templates are having same field section name, then when a template inherits from these two templates, similar field sections are merged, and all the fields under them are consolidated.</li>
<li>We should avoid Circular templates. for example, Template A can inherit from Templates B and C. Template C can inherit from Template A, too.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://gettingtoknowsitecore.blogspot.in/2010/01/inheritance-content-modeling-sitecore.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://gettingtoknowsitecore.blogspot.in/2010/01/inheritance-content-modeling-sitecore.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.matthewdresser.com/sitecore/template-inheritance-best-practices" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.matthewdresser.com/sitecore/template-inheritance-best-practices</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.in/Professional-Sitecore-Development-WROX-John/dp/812653673X" target="_blank" rel="external">Professional Sitecore Development</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.in/Professional-Sitecore-Development-Solutions-Practices/dp/1484222911" target="_blank" rel="external">Professional Sitecore 8 Development: A Complete Guide to Solutions and Best Practices</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Template_Inheritance&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Template_Inheritance&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Template Inheritance&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Template Inheritance&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sitecore Web Content Management System with .NET</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Web-CMS-with-.NET/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-Web-CMS-with-.NET/</id>
    <published>2017-02-22T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-22T04:23:59.073Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="First_presentation_in_-NET_User_Group_Bangalore"><a href="#First_presentation_in_-NET_User_Group_Bangalore" class="headerlink" title="First presentation in .NET User Group Bangalore"></a>First presentation in .NET User Group Bangalore</h4><p>I am regular attendee to <a href="https://www.meetup.com/DotNetBLR/" target="_blank" rel="external">.NET User Group Bangalore</a>. It was always my wish to present in the meetup.</p>
<p>At last, recently I had given my first presentation in .NET User Group Bangalore, It was wonderful experience of preparing, practicing, and delivering it in front of audience.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/dotnetblrQ1-2017.jpg" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Presentation_Deck_3A"><a href="#Presentation_Deck_3A" class="headerlink" title="Presentation Deck:"></a>Presentation Deck:</h5>
	<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/crJIXdf8vGLkUP" style="width:100%;height:550px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen> </iframe> <div style="margin-bottom:5px">


<h5 id="Recorded_Video_3A"><a href="#Recorded_Video_3A" class="headerlink" title="Recorded Video:"></a>Recorded Video:</h5><div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RzM1DzjneL8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p>More details about the talk can be found <a href="https://www.meetup.com/DotNetBLR/events/236111732/" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a></p>
<p>Thanks to Surendra, <a href="https://twitter.com/andhrachowdary" target="_blank" rel="external">Haribabu</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/anandgothe" target="_blank" rel="external">Anand Gothe</a> for their support and encouragement.</p>
</div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;First_presentation_in_-NET_User_Group_Bangalore&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#First_presentation_in_-NET_User_Group_Bangalore&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Talks" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Talks/"/>
    
    
      <category term=".NET User Group" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/NET-User-Group/"/>
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Presentation" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Presentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sitecore - Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-FAQ/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Sitecore-FAQ/</id>
    <published>2017-02-12T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:06.770Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly one and half year back When I started learning Sitecore as a <strong>.Net developer</strong> few questions were in my mind. Now I feel like I’m able to answer all those by adding some more questions asked by participants in last week presentation in <a href="https://www.meetup.com/DotNetBLR/events/236111732/" target="_blank" rel="external">Dotnet Bangalore user group</a>.</p>
<h5 id="1-_What_is_CMS/WCMS_3F"><a href="#1-_What_is_CMS/WCMS_3F" class="headerlink" title="1. What is CMS/WCMS?"></a>1. What is CMS/WCMS?</h5><p>If we break CMS (Content Management System) into pieces,</p>
<p><strong>Content:</strong> Content is a resource; it can be document, pdf, image, audio, or video file etc.<br><strong>Management:</strong> Organizing (add/update/delete) the content.<br><strong>System:</strong> Application/Platform which helps to manage the content.</p>
<p>Let’s combine 3 pieces for definition,<br><strong>Content Management System (CMS):</strong> CMS is a system which helps to manage the content.<br><strong>Web Content Management System (CMS):</strong> WCMS is a system which helps to manage the content, via web interface.</p>
<h5 id="2-_What_problem_Content_Management_systems_are_trying_to_solve_3F"><a href="#2-_What_problem_Content_Management_systems_are_trying_to_solve_3F" class="headerlink" title="2. What problem Content Management systems are trying to solve?"></a>2. What problem Content Management systems are trying to solve?</h5><p>In very high level note, we can categorize websites into <strong>Static</strong> &amp; <strong>Dynamic</strong> sites,<br>In Static Sites content is not changed so frequently, but whereas in Dynamic sites, content need to be updated very frequently.<br>There is no easy way for business people to update the content. As a developer, we can provide an option to business users to update the content by providing them Admin interfaces. But with this option, there is a risk of building and maintaining the Admin interfaces, and there is a lot of time involved in it. What if someone else provide the interfaces, we can concentrate on core development of building the website.<br>This is where <strong>Content Management Systems</strong> come into picture. Content Management System helps business users (non-technical) to easily manage their content via web interface.</p>
<h5 id="3-_What_is_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#3-_What_is_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="3. What is Sitecore?"></a>3. What is Sitecore?</h5><p>Sitecore at its essence is a Content Management System, but it is much more than that. “Sitecore Experience Platform is a ‘blended’ solution – it combines web content management with a marketing platform.”<br>Sitecore provides an end to end solution which deals with Content management system and Digital marketing system under one platform as per corporate needs.<br><img src="/css/images/sitecoreexperienceplatform.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="4-_I_am_a_-NET_developer_2C_am_I_suitable_for_Sitecore_development_3F"><a href="#4-_I_am_a_-NET_developer_2C_am_I_suitable_for_Sitecore_development_3F" class="headerlink" title="4. I am a .NET developer, am I suitable for Sitecore development?"></a>4. I am a .NET developer, am I suitable for Sitecore development?</h5><p>Yes, As Sitecore is built on .NET stack, it is best suited for .NET developer to learn and work on Sitecore implementations.</p>
<h5 id="5-_As_a_-NET_developer_2C_how_does_it_benefit_to_learn_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#5-_As_a_-NET_developer_2C_how_does_it_benefit_to_learn_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="5. As a .NET developer, how does it benefit to learn Sitecore?"></a>5. As a .NET developer, how does it benefit to learn Sitecore?</h5><p>There are around <strong>4,900+</strong> brands are using Sitecore, and more and more brands are embracing Sitecore. So, more demand for Sitecore developers. As a developer it is good career option to explore, and importantly, you will still be working on .NET tech stack.</p>
<h5 id="6-_Pre-requisites_to_start_learning_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#6-_Pre-requisites_to_start_learning_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="6. Pre-requisites to start learning Sitecore?"></a>6. Pre-requisites to start learning Sitecore?</h5><p>Decent amount of knowledge on the .NET technologies, like ASP.NET MVC/Web forms, C#, SQL server (although mostly we don’t write SQL queries), and basic understanding of HTML, JavaScript and JQuery.</p>
<h5 id="7-_Where_will_I_get_Sitecore_documentation_3F"><a href="#7-_Where_will_I_get_Sitecore_documentation_3F" class="headerlink" title="7. Where will I get Sitecore documentation?"></a>7. Where will I get Sitecore documentation?</h5><p>Please refer official <a href="https://doc.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore documentation</a>.</p>
<h5 id="8-_Sitecore_2C_Is_it_free_3F"><a href="#8-_Sitecore_2C_Is_it_free_3F" class="headerlink" title="8. Sitecore, Is it free?"></a>8. Sitecore, Is it free?</h5><p>No, it comes with license fee. Code is also not open source.</p>
<h5 id="10-_Some_of_the_Indian_companies_2C_where_they_recruit_Sitecore_developers_3F"><a href="#10-_Some_of_the_Indian_companies_2C_where_they_recruit_Sitecore_developers_3F" class="headerlink" title="10. Some of the Indian companies, where they recruit Sitecore developers?"></a>10. Some of the Indian companies, where they recruit Sitecore developers?</h5><p>As per my knowledge, following are some of the organizations,</p>
<ul>
<li>Verndale</li>
<li>Epsilon</li>
<li>Sapient</li>
<li>Accenture</li>
<li>Mindtree</li>
<li>HCL</li>
<li>Unicolumn Software PVT LTD,</li>
<li>Horizontal Integration<br>  For more info, explore <a href="http://www.sitecore.net/en/getting-started/partners/search-partners" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.sitecore.net/en/getting-started/partners/search-partners</a></li>
</ul>
<h5 id="11-_From_-NET_background_2C_where_should_I_start_learning_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#11-_From_-NET_background_2C_where_should_I_start_learning_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="11. From .NET background, where should I start learning Sitecore?"></a>11. From .NET background, where should I start learning Sitecore?</h5><p>Sitecore recently launched a foundation course called <strong><a href="https://elearning.sitecore.net/public/ContentDetails.aspx?id=7B781B1C3510447BBA22D7B0BF3251A2" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore Developer Foundations</a></strong>, which is free, and covers Sitecore basics. Although course is free, you need a license to practice, you can approach Sitecore sales/support to get further information on trial license.</p>
<h5 id="12-_Can_I_develop_my_personal_website_on_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#12-_Can_I_develop_my_personal_website_on_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="12. Can I develop my personal website on Sitecore?"></a>12. Can I develop my personal website on Sitecore?</h5><p>Sitecore XP is an Enterprise level Content Management system, it is overkill to use it for personal websites. It is not free; you need to pay license fee.</p>
<h5 id="13-_What_are_all_the_Sitecore_databases_3F"><a href="#13-_What_are_all_the_Sitecore_databases_3F" class="headerlink" title="13. What are all the Sitecore databases?"></a>13. What are all the Sitecore databases?</h5><p>On very light node Sitecore uses both SQL Server (minimal support to Oracle) and Mongo DB databases; SQL Server databases are for content, and Mongo DB databases for analytics. You can find more details <a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/">here</a>.</p>
<h5 id="14-_Can_I_modify_Sitecore_databases_Schema_3F"><a href="#14-_Can_I_modify_Sitecore_databases_Schema_3F" class="headerlink" title="14. Can I modify Sitecore databases Schema?"></a>14. Can I modify Sitecore databases Schema?</h5><p>It is not advisable, if any extra tables are required we can create a custom database, and use it.</p>
<h5 id="15-_Can_Sitecore_solutions_be_deployed_on_Cloud_3F"><a href="#15-_Can_Sitecore_solutions_be_deployed_on_Cloud_3F" class="headerlink" title="15. Can Sitecore solutions be deployed on Cloud?"></a>15. Can Sitecore solutions be deployed on Cloud?</h5><p>Yes, previously you can do it only using Infrastructure As a Service (IAAS), but recently Sitecore by collaborating with Microsoft, released Platform As a Service (PAAS) tools. Now we can easily deploy using PAAS as well.</p>
<h5 id="16-_Is_Sitecore_available_as_Software_As_a_Service__28SAAS_29_3F"><a href="#16-_Is_Sitecore_available_as_Software_As_a_Service__28SAAS_29_3F" class="headerlink" title="16. Is Sitecore available as Software As a Service (SAAS)?"></a>16. Is Sitecore available as Software As a Service (SAAS)?</h5><p>No, Sitecore is not a portal kind of solution, which can be used as SAAS. Sitecore provides a platform for developers to implement Sitecore solutions, clients can not directly use Sitecore vanilla version.</p>
<h5 id="17-_How_can_I_create_user_input_forms_in_Sitecore_3F"><a href="#17-_How_can_I_create_user_input_forms_in_Sitecore_3F" class="headerlink" title="17. How can I create user input forms in Sitecore?"></a>17. How can I create user input forms in Sitecore?</h5><p>Sitecore provides Web Forms For Marketers (WFFM) module, using which you can create simple web forms that record and report information provided by visitors to your website.</p>
<h5 id="18-_Where_does_Sitecore_stores_content_managed_images_3F"><a href="#18-_Where_does_Sitecore_stores_content_managed_images_3F" class="headerlink" title="18. Where does Sitecore stores content managed images?"></a>18. Where does Sitecore stores content managed images?</h5><p>Sitecore provides two options; In Database or file system; Options are configurable.</p>
<h5 id="19-_Where_does_Sitecore_stores_content_managed_Videos_3F"><a href="#19-_Where_does_Sitecore_stores_content_managed_Videos_3F" class="headerlink" title="19. Where does Sitecore stores content managed Videos?"></a>19. Where does Sitecore stores content managed Videos?</h5><p>Usually videos are integrated from external media platforms like Brightcove, Ooyala, YouTube, and Vimeo etc. Only Video information gets imported into Sitecore, not the Video file.</p>
<h5 id="20-_Are_there_any_Sitecore_developer_certifications_3F"><a href="#20-_Are_there_any_Sitecore_developer_certifications_3F" class="headerlink" title="20. Are there any Sitecore developer certifications?"></a>20. Are there any Sitecore developer certifications?</h5><p>Yes, there is a <strong>Sitecore Professional Developer Certification</strong>, which developer get <strong>Sitecore Certified Professional Developer</strong> title.</p>
<p>Will keep adding more questions and answers.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Exactly one and half year back When I started learning Sitecore as a &lt;strong&gt;.Net developer&lt;/strong&gt; few questions were in my mind. Now I
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates Part 4 (Link Field Types)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-4/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-4/</id>
    <published>2017-02-04T02:47:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:06.996Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Link_Field_Types"><a href="#Link_Field_Types" class="headerlink" title="Link Field Types"></a>Link Field Types</h4><p>This is the fourth post as part of <a href="/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/">Sitecore Template series</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore 8.2 (rev. 160729)</strong></p>
<p>In last two posts, we discussed about <a href="/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-2/">Simple field types</a> &amp; <a href="/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-3/">List field types</a>, now let’s look into <strong>Link</strong> field types.</p>
<h5 id="Link_types_3A"><a href="#Link_types_3A" class="headerlink" title="Link types:"></a>Link types:</h5><p>Link field types allow content authors to enter links to Sitecore internal items, external URLs, anchors, and email addresses.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-link-types.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Droplink:</strong> Similar to the Droplist field type, which we had seen in the previous <a href="/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-3/">post</a>, this field type also allows the content author to select a single item from the list specified by the source property of the field. If the source is not set, no items are shown in the drop-down.<br><em>Field source can be set while declaring the field, using Source property.</em><br><em>Raw value:</em> Selected Item GUID<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.RefernceField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, and XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/droplink-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/droplink-field-type-without-source.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Droptree:</strong> This field type also allows the content author to select a single item from the list specified by the source property of the field. Items are shown in tree-view rather than the normal drop-down. If the source is not set, it shows the entire tree.<br><em>Raw value:</em> Selected Item GUID<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.RefernceField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, and XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/droptree-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/droptree-field-type-without-source.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>General Link:</strong> This is the most frequently used link field type. This type allows content authors to link to a Sitecore item, an external URL, an anchor, an email address, or a JavaScript function.<br><em>Raw value:</em> XHTML<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.LinkField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/general-link-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>General Link with Search:</strong> This is similar to General Link field type, except that this one is having an extra link search functionality. Using this, content authors can search (for Internal link) and link to items.<br><em>Recently we come across a scenario where clients want to search for an item to link, because it is tedious for them to navigate to that item, (we can use other field types, but they want to ) this field type came to our rescue :)</em><br><em>Raw value:</em> XHTML<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.LinkField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/general-link-with-search-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p> <strong>Version Identity:</strong> and <strong>Version Link:</strong> field types are used by Sitecore for internal purposes.</p>
<p>Till now we looked into Simple, List, and field types. But there are other field types which are not so frequently  used by developers.</p>
<ul>
<li>Analytics</li>
<li>Social</li>
<li>Developer Types</li>
<li>System Types</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Raw value: A value which gets stored in the database for each field.<br>Field type class: Using which developer can access the field values.<br>Field Renderer supported: Field type has corresponding FieldRenderer web control, when used, content authors can use Experience editor to manage the content for particular field.</em></p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Link_Field_Types&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Link_Field_Types&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Link Field Types&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Link Field Types&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the fo
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore Field Types" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore-Field-Types/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Verndale Steps Challenge - 2017</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Verndale-Steps-Challenge-2017/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/02/Verndale-Steps-Challenge-2017/</id>
    <published>2017-02-04T00:47:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-11T01:52:25.797Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Verndale_Steps_Challenge_participation_Experience"><a href="#Verndale_Steps_Challenge_participation_Experience" class="headerlink" title="Verndale Steps Challenge participation Experience"></a>Verndale Steps Challenge participation Experience</h4><p>From childhood I always love walking and running. Walking gives me pleasure, releases my stress, and improves my thinking. Even though I love walking, I am not regular about it, only when I feel to walk, then only I do it. Sometimes if I am stuck up on something, like need to take a critical decision, or to resolve an issue, then walking helps me to think clearly. After I became a Software engineer, Walking helped me to solve lot of developer road blocks.</p>
<p>Around 4 months back (Sep-2016), my friend from USA gifted me with Power beats wireless earphones, and jawbone Up fitness tracker. once I received both of them, started morning walk for couple twice a week, with 2 to 3 km distance at a time.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/powerbeats.jpg" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/jawbone-up.jpg" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Verndale_Steps_Challenge"><a href="#Verndale_Steps_Challenge" class="headerlink" title="Verndale Steps Challenge"></a>Verndale Steps Challenge</h5><p>In December-2016, there was an announcement in office, about holding a month long, companywide steps and run challenge. The challenge is based on the number of miles walked or ran. Immediately, I was interested to participate in steps challenge, and signed up for it. This challenge is going to be tracked on Endomondo (a free fitness app). so downloaded the app, and ready for the challenge.</p>
<p>While signing up, my thoughts are like, anyway I am going to morning walk for twice a week. So for this challenge, will make it regular, and increase the distance up to 5 km per day, that may give chance to top in the list. So daily 5km, means end of the month it will be 150km, this will be more than enough. (<em>Little did I know that, 150km is no where near, and I will finish the challenge with 510km.</em>)</p>
<p>Challenge runs from <strong>3rd Jan 2017</strong> to <strong>3rd Feb 2017</strong>. But I started regular walk from 2nd Jan (1 day before), to see whether I can actually walk for 5km in a single workout. It was ok, I was able to walk 5km with ease, and felt good about it.</p>
<p>Once Challenge is started, and many of my Bangalore colleagues also signed up for it, so in tea time, we used to have fun discussion about the challenge. These discussions continued for whole month.</p>
<p><strong>First time 10km walk</strong> After initial days of the challenge are over, understood that 5km are not going to be enough. One day wanted to try for 10km, I know that It’s very long for a single workout. Somehow believed, I could make it. By the time I reached 7-8 km, my legs are paining like hell, thought of giving up there, but don’t know what happened, I was determined to finish that 10kms. Pushed myself for another 2kms, and was able to finish 10 km. This is one of the most memorable experience, in the whole journey. Looking back, I feel proud of myself, that I could cross that 10kms.<br><img src="/css/images/endomondo-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Later 10km became a regular distance for my workout. As the days are passing, intensity in the competition has also increased, I also needed to keep up my pace.</p>
<p><strong>Lake park:</strong> I like walking beside the lake, love the morning breeze, sunrise, and everything around there. Every day I had some wonderful experience there, like meeting new people, and inspired by some of their determination. When I go for walk in other parks, I couldn’t spend so much time there, as I don’t get the same breeze, always wish to go to lake park.</p>
<p><strong>Music &amp; Podcasts:</strong> Power beats are very useful in this journey. While walking, I love to listen Music, especially Telugu (mother tongue) songs. But this time I also explored another stream which are podcasts. I know about podcasts before, but here and there I used to listen only an episode from <a href="/(http://hanselminutes.com/">Hansel minutes</a>) podcast. This time, as I am walking long distances, wanted to explore podcasts fully. I listened to some of the wonderful episodes from different podcasts, and now I am following lot of good podcasts like,</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://coresampler.fireside.fm/" target="_blank" rel="external">CoreSampler</a></li>
<li><a href="http://hanselminutes.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Hansel Minutes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://wildermuth.com/hwpod" target="_blank" rel="external">Hello World Podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.dotnetrocks.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">.NET Rocks</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.podcasts.com/telugu-bytes" target="_blank" rel="external">Telugu Bytes</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I also listened to <strong>Anthem</strong> by Ayn Rand audio book.</p>
<p><strong>Last day of the challenge</strong> I wanted to finish it on a high note, in morning I increased my pace, and reached  maximum single workout distance of <strong>17km</strong>, and also maximum distance per day <strong>27.5km</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/jawbone-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Irrespective of the result, by participating in this challenge, I am left with so many wonderful memories, and first time covered 10km, 15km, and 17km distance. In my wildest thoughts also, I would have not guessed, that I can walk for <strong>510km</strong> in a month. It made to me to push my limits in all possible ways.</p>
<p>Image courtesy</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.audiosplitz.com/2016/04/beats-powerbeats2-wireless.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.audiosplitz.com/2016/04/beats-powerbeats2-wireless.html</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Verndale_Steps_Challenge_participation_Experience&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Verndale_Steps_Challenge_participation_Experience&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; t
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Walking" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Walking/"/>
    
      <category term="Workout" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Workout/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates Part 3 (List Field Types)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-3/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-3/</id>
    <published>2017-01-28T02:47:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:06:06.973Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="List_Field_Types"><a href="#List_Field_Types" class="headerlink" title="List Field Types"></a>List Field Types</h4><p>This is the third post as part of <a href="/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/">Sitecore Template series</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore 8.2 (rev. 160729)</strong></p>
<p>In the previous <a href="/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-2/">post</a>, we discussed about Simple field types, in this post let’s look into <strong>List</strong> field types.</p>
<h5 id="List_types_3A"><a href="#List_types_3A" class="headerlink" title="List types:"></a>List types:</h5><p>List type fields allow content authors to select one or multiple values, ex: countries, categories, etc.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-list-types.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multilist:</strong> This is one of the most commonly used list type, using this type, content authors can choose one or more items, from the list, which are based on the source property of the field specified. If the field source is not specified, selectable list becomes empty. <em>Field source can be set while declaring the field, using Source property.</em><br><em>Raw value:</em> Pipe separated GUID’s<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.MultilistField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, and XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/multilist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/multilist-field-type-without-source.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multilist with Search:</strong> This is similar to Multilist field type, but having a search functionality. When there are large number of selectable items, this field type aids content authors to search and choose items.<br><em>Raw value:</em> Pipe separated GUID’s<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.MultilistField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, and XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/multilist-with-search-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Treelist:</strong> This list type, lists all the selectable items in tree structure, including the parent item. If no source is specified, it will list whole Sitecore tree.<br><em>Raw value:</em> Pipe separated GUID’s<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.MultilistField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query, and query string</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/treelist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/treelist-field-type-without-source.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>TreelistEx:</strong> This is pretty much similar to Treelist, except that for this field type, the selection option will be opened in a new browser window (pop up); when no source is specified, this also lists the entire tree. TreelistEx field type performance is better than Treelist field type, because for TreelistEx, the client renders only the list of selected items, and does not render the selection tree until the user clicks the Edit command which is present above the field.<br><em>Raw value:</em> Pipe separated GUID’s<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.MultilistField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query, and query string</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/treelistex-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Checklist:</strong> The list type allows the user to select one or more checkboxes representing the children of the item specified by Source property of the field. Unlike other list types, content authors cannot order their selection.<br><em>Raw value:</em> Pipe separated GUID’s<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.MultilistField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/checklist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Droplist:</strong> The Droplist field type allows the content author to select a single item from the list specified by the Source property of the field.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string (name of the selected item)<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/droplist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Grouped Droplist:</strong> This field type allows content author to select a single grandchild of the item specified by Source property of the field. This type stores the name of selected item.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string (name of the selected item)<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/groupeddroplist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Grouped Droplink:</strong> This is very much similar to Grouped Droplist field type, except that, The Grouped Droplink field type stores the GUID of the selected item.<br><em>Raw value:</em> GUID (ID of the selected item)<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.ReferenceField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No<br><em>Allowed format in source field property:</em> GUID, Path, XPath Query</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/groupeddroplink-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Name Value List:</strong> This field type allows the content authors to enter values in key-value pairs. When first key, value pair is entered, another row will appear to enter next set of values. Sitecore stores the values entered as a list of key=value pairs separated by ampersands (“&amp;”). I had seen this in real time for Brightcove media framework, for each Brightcove video item, we have custom fields getting imported in name-value pairs.<br><em>Raw value:</em> key=value pairs separated by ampersands (“&amp;”)<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.NameValueListField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/namevaluelist-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Name Lookup Value List:</strong> This field type is similar to Name Value List field type, in Name Value List, content author has to enter both key &amp; value pair, but here content authors enters keys, and for value choose an item from populated drop-down list.<br><em>Raw value:</em> key=value pairs separated by ampersands (“&amp;”)<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.NameValueListField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Raw value: A value which gets stored in the database for each field.<br>Field type class: Using which developer can access the field values.<br>Field Renderer supported: Field type has corresponding FieldRenderer web control, when used, content authors can use Experience editor to manage the content for particular field.</em></p>
<p>In next post, will look into Link types.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://getfishtank.ca/blog/treelist-data-source-hidden-functionality" target="_blank" rel="external">http://getfishtank.ca/blog/treelist-data-source-hidden-functionality</a></li>
<li><a href="https://exploringsitecore.wordpress.com/category/sitecore/name-value-list-sitecore/" target="_blank" rel="external">https://exploringsitecore.wordpress.com/category/sitecore/name-value-list-sitecore/</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;List_Field_Types&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#List_Field_Types&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;List Field Types&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;List Field Types&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the th
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore Field Types" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore-Field-Types/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates Part 2 (Simple Field Types)</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-2/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-2/</id>
    <published>2017-01-21T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.338Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Template_Fields"><a href="#Template_Fields" class="headerlink" title="Template Fields"></a>Template Fields</h4><p>This is the second post as part of <a href="/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/">Sitecore Template series</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Sitecore 8.2 (rev. 160729)</strong></p>
<p>In this post, let’s discuss about fields, and their types. If we think of a <em>template</em> as a <em>class</em>, then <em>fields</em> are <em>properties</em> of that class. We can consider each field is container for the individual piece of content (image, link, text, list, etc.), and using this fields Content Authors can add/update their content.</p>
<p>How each property of the class has its own type, similar way each template field also has its own field type. Field type determines, three things</p>
<ol>
<li>What type of content (normal text, rich text, image etc.) can be entered into the field,</li>
<li>What type of control (Single line text, Rich text editor, etc.) need to be shown to content authors to enter their data,</li>
<li>In what format the value is stored in the database.</li>
</ol>
<p>Out of the box Sitecore provides lot of field types, but based on the requirement, developers can create custom field types. From requirements, or from design, developer has to infer the fields &amp; corresponding field types required for particular page, or module.</p>
<p>We can classify/categorize field types as shown below,</p>
<ul>
<li>Simple types</li>
<li>List types</li>
<li>Link types</li>
</ul>
<p>Let’s look into each type in detail,</p>
<h5 id="Simple_types_3A"><a href="#Simple_types_3A" class="headerlink" title="Simple types:"></a>Simple types:</h5><p>The Simple type field contains individual values, like a text, integer, or date value.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-simple-types.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Single-Line Text:</strong> This is one of the most commonly used field type, and also the simplest one. It is similar to a HTML textbox control, and allows content authors to enter simple text.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/single-line-text.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi-Line Text:</strong> As the name suggests this type is used when we have multiple lines of text/comments to be added. This is similar to HTML textarea control.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/multi-line-text.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rich Text:</strong> This field type allows content authors to enter large text with media items, and also allows to modify HTML. This is similar to WYSIWYG editor.<br><em>Raw value:</em> XHTML<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/rich-text.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Integer:</strong> This field type allows content authors to enter whole number. It’s also similar to HTML textbox control.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/integer-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Number:</strong> This field type allows content authors to enter decimal values. It’s also similar to HTML textbox control.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/number-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Password:</strong> This field type is used for passwords, where characters in the field are masked. It is similar to HTML input control with password type.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.TextField</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/password-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Date &amp; Date Time:</strong> As the name suggests both of these field types are used for date &amp; date time respectively. This field types allow content authors to select or manually enter the data and time. These are similar to HTML input control with date type.<br><em>Raw value:</em> string (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO_8601" target="_blank" rel="external">ISO 8601</a> formatted date-time, <strong>yyyyMMddThhmmss</strong>)<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.DateField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/date-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Checkbox:</strong> This field type allows content authors to check/uncheck a particular value, and it’s similar to HTML input control with checkbox type. It contains either 0 or 1 value.<br><em>Raw value:</em> 0 or 1<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.CheckboxField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/checkbox-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Image:</strong> This field type allows content authors to select an image from the media library and specify image properties.<br><em>Raw value:</em> xml<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.ImageField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> Yes</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/image-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>File:</strong> This field type allows the user to select an item in the media library. Users can click Open file to open the Media Browser and select the desired file from the media library.<br>We can use the Source property of a File field to control the media folder selected when the content author opens the Media Browser, or to specify the root item for this selection interface.<br><em>Raw value:</em> xml<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.FileField<br><em>Field Renderer supported:</em> No</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/file-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Word Document:</strong> The Word Document field type allows the content authors to edit HTML using Microsoft Word embedded in the browser. (I have not yet used this field, and it is only supported in IE browser)<br><em>Raw value:</em> xml<br><em>Field type class:</em> Sitecore.Data.Fields.WordDocumentField</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/word-document-field-type.png" alt=""></p>
<p><em>Raw value: A value which gets stored in the database for each field.<br>Field type class: Using which developer can access the field values.<br>Field Renderer supported: Field type has corresponding FieldRenderer web control, when used, content authors can use Experience editor to manage the content for particular field.</em></p>
<p>In coming posts, will look into List and Link types.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">https://sdn.sitecore.net/upload/sitecore6/65/data_definition_reference_sc64-65-usletter.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.mtelligent.com/home/2014/8/29/sitecore-field-type-overview-reference.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://getfishtank.ca/blog/using-date-and-datetime-fields-in-sitecore" target="_blank" rel="external">http://getfishtank.ca/blog/using-date-and-datetime-fields-in-sitecore</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Template_Fields&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Template_Fields&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Template Fields&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Template Fields&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the second
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore Field Types" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore-Field-Types/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Enhancing Content Author Experience</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2017/01/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Enhancing-Content-Author-Experience/</id>
    <published>2017-01-14T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T07:24:26.853Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="Experience_on_giving_first_talk_in_Sitecore_User_Group_Bangalore"><a href="#Experience_on_giving_first_talk_in_Sitecore_User_Group_Bangalore" class="headerlink" title="Experience on giving first talk in Sitecore User Group Bangalore"></a>Experience on giving first talk in Sitecore User Group Bangalore</h4><p>Back after a month break, from next week we will restart our <a href="/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/">Sitecore Saturday learning series</a>. This week I am going to share my experiences on giving first ever presentation in any technical user group.</p>
<p>Previously I had experience on giving presentations either within the team, or within the organization, but never in any technical user group.</p>
<p>I regularly participate in technical user groups, in and around Bangalore, and also in some of the virtual user groups (webinars). This expands my knowledge, helps in understanding new trends, buzzwords, and also to update my skills.</p>
<p>In last November, I had given a Sitecore knowledge share session in my organization. As my friends were also interested in the topic, then got the idea of why not give this session in Sitecore user group, but this is completely out of my comfort zone.</p>
<p>Lot of thoughts runs in my mind, previously also many times got the same idea, but every time dropped it because of my discomfort. This time there was an urge to do it at any cost.</p>
<blockquote><p>Always do what you are afraid to do.</p>
<footer><strong>-Ralph Waldo Emerson</strong></footer></blockquote>
<p><img src="/css/images/firsttechtalkwebinar.jpg" alt=""></p>
<p>After much deliberation, one day mailed my willingness to present, and other relevant information to SUG Bangalore. <a href="https://techmusingz.wordpress.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Annie</a> was very encouraging, and also gave some tips on presentation. After a short communication through emails we decided on a date (07-January-2017) and announced it. By that time, I had finished with presentation deck, and local demo site, and also practiced the talk to follow time constraint (should have practiced more).</p>
<p>As it is a Webinar, one day before, we did a dry run in my system, and all set for go live. On 7th morning when I woke up to practice once more, my demo site is down. It was just 2 hours before the session, there are only two options, either setup the site again, or make the existing site up. I choose the first option, as there was not much time in digging the issue. Quickly I had setup the site again (thanks to Sitecore Instance Manager), and created all the necessary items.</p>
<p>In my area power is not so reliable, so decided to give the talk from office. Going to office on Saturdays is completely different experience, thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/andhrachowdary" target="_blank" rel="external">Haribabu</a> for accompanying me. When session started, I was lot nervous, slowly getting into comfort zone with ease. As it is a webinar (can’t see audience faces), I couldn’t decide exactly on where I need to slow down, or increase my speed, and same case with screen zoom in or zoom out. But somehow I was able to finish up within the time.</p>
<p>Only two things are in my mind while preparing &amp; giving the presentation,</p>
<ul>
<li>Should not give any misleading or false information.</li>
<li>Try to be relevant to the targeted audience as much as possible.</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope my session was useful at least to one person, then my target is accomplished.</p>
<h5 id="Presentation_Deck_3A"><a href="#Presentation_Deck_3A" class="headerlink" title="Presentation Deck:"></a>Presentation Deck:</h5>
	<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/3DXip4c4eVm2Rq" style="width:100%;height:550px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen> </iframe> <div style="margin-bottom:5px">


<h5 id="Webinar_Video_3A"><a href="#Webinar_Video_3A" class="headerlink" title="Webinar Video:"></a>Webinar Video:</h5><div class="video-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z1XlDGEZk6w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p>More details about the talk can be found <a href="http://sitecoreug.org/en/usergroups/bangalore-sitecore-user-group/events/january-2017/" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a></p>
<p>In coming months, some of the topics I am thinking of presenting are,</p>
<ul>
<li>Sitecore Media Framework with Brightcove (Two parts)</li>
<li>Sitecore Goals from Developer perspective</li>
<li>Search: Absolute basics</li>
<li>Niche topics: Sitemap, SEO Metadata, URL redirects, 400 not found, 500 server error page, and RSS feeds.</li>
<li>Sitecore What, Why &amp; How: For .NET developers who never heard of Sitecore.</li>
<li>T4 templates &amp; code generation.</li>
</ul>
<p>User groups I regularly participate are,</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sitecoreug.org/usergroups/bangalore-sitecore-user-group/" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore User Group Bangalore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/BDotNet/" target="_blank" rel="external">BDotnet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/dotnetblr/" target="_blank" rel="external">Dotnet Bangalore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/SoftwareArchitectsBangalore/" target="_blank" rel="external">Software Architects Bangalore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Microsoft-Azure-Bangalore/" target="_blank" rel="external">Microsoft Azure User Group-Bangalore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/ScrumBangalore/" target="_blank" rel="external">Scrum Bangalore</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://techmusingz.wordpress.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Annie</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/andhrachowdary" target="_blank" rel="external">Haribabu</a> for their support and encouragement.</p>
</div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h4 id=&quot;Experience_on_giving_first_talk_in_Sitecore_User_Group_Bangalore&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Experience_on_giving_first_talk_in_Sitecore_User_Group_B
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Talks" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Talks/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Presentation" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Presentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore User Group" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore-User-Group/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Templates Part-1</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-1/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Template-Part-1/</id>
    <published>2016-12-10T07:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.309Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of <a href="/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/">Saturday Sitecore Learning series</a>, till now we looked into,</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-CMS/">What is CMS?</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/06/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-About-Sitecore/">What is Sitecore?</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/">Sitecore installation</a> (I prefer using SIM)</li>
<li><a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/">Setting up Visual Studio Solution</a> (Outside webroot)</li>
<li><a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/">About Sitecore Databases</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/">Exploring Default home page</a></li>
</ul>
<p>By this time, I assume that you have both Sitecore and Visual Studio project setups in your machine, If not, please go through these two posts, <a href="/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/">Sitecore installation</a>, <a href="/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/">Setting up Visual Studio Solution</a> and try setting them up.</p>
<p>From now onwards we will look into core Sitecore concepts in more detail manner.</p>
<p>First let’s explore one of the important part of Sitecore, which are Templates. Understanding the Templates, is very important for developers, as selecting the correct template type, dictates overall experience of managing content. Templates is a very vast topic, and can’t be covered in a single post, so it will be spanning across multiple posts.</p>
<h4 id="Template_Fundamentals"><a href="#Template_Fundamentals" class="headerlink" title="Template Fundamentals"></a>Template Fundamentals</h4><p>Templates, also commonly referred as <strong>Data Templates</strong>, which are basic building blocks of any content in Sitecore. Every piece of content (page or components) in Sitecore needs a data template to define what it is.</p>
<p>To understand it better, Templates can be compared to Class (In object oriented programming) definitions,</p>
<ul>
<li>Each Class contain fields with their respective data types, similarly every Template contain fields, with their respective field types. (Ex: <em>Single-line text</em>)</li>
<li>Any number of instances can be created based on a class, similarly we can create any number of content items based on a single template.</li>
<li>Class supports inheritance, similarly templates also supports inheritance, in which a single template can inherit from multiple base templates, to mainly share the common fields.</li>
</ul>
<p>Before creating any content, first we need to create a Template with fields and their types. In a nutshell, Templates specify the data fields and many other settings that can be applied to content upon creation.</p>
<p>All Templates are defined under <em>/sitecore/templates</em> in Sitecore tree structure.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/templates-tree.png" alt=""></p>
<p>To open templates, we can open them either from Content Editor, or from Template Navigator, which is present in Start menu. (Start menu is available in Desktop mode)</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-manager.png" alt=""></p>
<p>While exploring <a href="/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/">default home page</a>, we noticed that home page content item, is using Sample item template, which can be found in <em>/sitecore/templates/Sample/Sample Item</em><br><img src="/css/images/default-home-template.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Following are some of the terms, we need to understand, before we do hands on creating templates. Let’s look into each of them more detail in coming up posts.</p>
<ul>
<li>Fields - Field Sections, Field Types, Field Source, and Field Validation.</li>
<li>Template Inheritance</li>
<li>Standard Values</li>
<li>Template types</li>
</ul>
<p>In next post we will look into Sitecore fields.</p>
<p><strong>References</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Professional Sitecore 8 development - <a href="http://www.apress.com/us/book/9781484222911" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.apress.com/us/book/9781484222911</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;As part of &lt;a href=&quot;/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/&quot;&gt;Saturday Sitecore Learning series&lt;/a&gt;, till now we looked into,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Templates" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/Templates/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Default Home Page</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/12/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Default-Home-Page/</id>
    <published>2016-12-03T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:20.889Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I explained on how to install Sitecore and setup new project in my previous posts, Now it’s time to drill down on the Sitecore default home page. Let’s explore it’s Template, Layout, sub-layout, Content Item etc. At last we will see how the Content Author can change the text using Content editor.</p>
<p>Before we move further, few of you may not be convenient with terminology (template, layout, sub-layout) but no issues just follow the steps, we will discuss more about each topic in coming posts.</p>
<p>If we load the newly installed Sitecore website, we can see the below page, as the website home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-default-homepage.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now let’s look into each and every aspect from Sitecore side, first let’s login into Sitecore using <strong>admin/b</strong> credentials,</p>
<p>From Launch pad, navigate to Content Editor, by directly clicking on the <strong>Content Editor</strong> option, or through <strong>Desktop</strong> option, it is a good practice to go from Desktop, as we can open multiple windows, and navigate among them, similar to windows desktop, and also having start menu. This is not possible by directly selecting Content Editor option from Launch pad.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-desktop.png" alt=""></p>
<p>If you click on Desktop mode, select Sitecore logo/start button and select “Content Editor” option.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/start-menu.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In Content Editor, navigate to the Home content item (<strong>/sitecore/content/Home</strong>),</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/default-home-content.png" alt=""></p>
<h4 id="Data_Template_3A"><a href="#Data_Template_3A" class="headerlink" title="Data Template:"></a>Data Template:</h4><p>In Sitecore, every content item is created from Template. Template contains field definition, and presentation information. Some say <em>“Templates are like class definitions. Content is like an instance of that class.”</em><br>In Sitecore tree, all the templates are present under <strong>sitecore/Templates</strong></p>
<p>For the default “Home” page Template is already present in Templates section. We can see the Template name, In Quick Info section, which is <strong>Sample Item</strong> in this case. By clicking on the template name, we can navigate to the template item.(if you opened in Desktop mode, Template will be opened in new window, else on the same window) or we can navigate to the template using its path <strong>/sitecore/templates/Sample/Sample Item</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-structure.png" alt=""></p>
<p>By looking into <strong>Sample Item</strong> Template’s <strong>Builder</strong> tab, we can understand that there are two fields defined in it, which are <strong>Title</strong> (text Type) and <strong>Text</strong> (Rich Text Type). <strong>Field Type</strong> determines the control to manage the content by content author using the editing interface.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-fields.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Standard Values</strong> for a particular template, lists all the fields including inherited fields. All the presentation details are assigned on Standard values.<br>For all the page templates, we have a presentation, where we can assign a layout and components (sub-layouts). On request of a web page, Sitecore assembles the page dynamically from it’s content and the presentation components.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/template-presentation.png" alt=""></p>
<h4 id="Presentation_3A"><a href="#Presentation_3A" class="headerlink" title="Presentation:"></a>Presentation:</h4><p>Now let’s look into presentation components, both layout, and sub layouts. All the layouts, sub layouts, renderings (in MVC), will be present under <strong>sitecore/Layout</strong> in the Sitecore tree.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layoust.png" alt=""></p>
<p>From <strong>Sample Item</strong> template presentation, we can see that there is one layout <strong>(Sample Layout)</strong>, and three components <strong>(Sample Sublayout, Sample Inner Sublayout,</strong> and <strong>Sample Rendering)</strong>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/presentation.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Let’s explore Sample Layout first, which is present in <strong>sitecore/Layout/Layouts/</strong> path. Layout is kind of master page in ASP.NET terminology, where we have basic html tags are added, and placeholders are defined. On Click of Sample Layout item, we can see the <strong>Path</strong> field, there is a .aspx page path is given, which contains all the HTML code with respect to the page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/main-layout.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layout-path.png" alt=""></p>
<p>If we observe the layout code, we can see that HTML tags are present and also a placeholder with key as <strong>main</strong> is added. This is the placeholder where, other page components are going to be embedded.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/layout-code.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Similar way if we look at <strong>Sample Sublayout</strong> item, which is under <strong>/sitecore/Layout/Sublayouts</strong>. This is an .ascx file.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sublayout.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sublayout-code.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Similar to this component, other page components also have code files with respect to them.<br>ASP.NET webforms -&gt; <strong>.ascx</strong> files<br>ASP.NET MVC -&gt; <strong>Controller</strong> rendering, or <strong>View</strong> rendering.<br>XSLT -&gt; XSL Rendering</p>
<p>If we look at the Sample rendering which is a xsl rendering, this is where we are rendering both the fields, <strong>‘title’ &amp; ‘text’</strong>, which are created in template.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/xslrendering.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/xslrenderingcode.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now let’s get back to our home item, where we have already content present for both the fields, which we can see on home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/conten-output.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Till now we have seen Templates, Standard values, presentation, layout, sub-layout and renderings. Stay tune to this space for my next posts to discuss more detail on each item we used in home page.</p>
<h4 id="Hello_World"><a href="#Hello_World" class="headerlink" title="Hello World"></a>Hello World</h4><p>We will try changing the Title field content to <strong>Hello World</strong>, and verify that text is changing on home page or not. After making any change, we need to publish the item; As I discussed earlier our changes will save in to Master database. On Click of publish latest modifications/final content gets pushed to <strong>web</strong> database. Refer Below screenshot for final output we are expecting. Hello world is indeed appearing on home page.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/helloworld-content.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Sitecore supports both ASP.NET web forms and MVC, but default home page comes with all web forms related code. Currently most of new Sitecore implementations are done in MVC. So in coming up posts, we will always try to see the code examples in MVC.<br>ASP.NET web forms is still very much in picture, because lot of implementations till now are done in web forms. Whenever we are maintaining those applications, web forms knowledge is very much required.<br>That’s all for this week.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;As I explained on how to install Sitecore and setup new project in my previous posts, Now it’s time to drill down on the Sitecore default
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Code review check list</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Basic-Code-Review-Checklist/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Basic-Code-Review-Checklist/</id>
    <published>2016-11-26T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.107Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I am going away from our series, and sharing the presentation on the Sitecore basic code review check list. This presentation deck is part of the knowledge share session, I had delivered in office.</p>
<p>This check list helps Sitecore developers to better enhance the Content Author experience in managing their content.</p>

	<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/xBecChQ8JHkFDL" style="width:100%;height:550px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen> </iframe> <div style="margin-bottom:5px">


<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
</div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;This week, I am going away from our series, and sharing the presentation on the Sitecore basic code review check list. This presentation 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Presentation" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Presentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Databases</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Databases/</id>
    <published>2016-11-19T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.135Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By this time, we have Sitecore website running in our machine, and also ready with Visual Studio solution setup. From now, we will look into Sitecore concepts, in both theory and hands on as well.<br>As we all know Sitecore is a database driven CMS, in this post let’s look into Sitecore databases.</p>
<h4 id="Sitecore_Databases_3A"><a href="#Sitecore_Databases_3A" class="headerlink" title="Sitecore Databases:"></a>Sitecore Databases:</h4><p>From developer’s perspective, until and unless any customization is required, we don’t directly deal with databases, we always access data using Sitecore Api’s. but it is very important to know about, what are all databases Sitecore uses.</p>
<p>Sitecore uses multiple databases to manage both content and also analytics related data.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-databases.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Content_Databases"><a href="#Content_Databases" class="headerlink" title="Content Databases"></a>Content Databases</h5><p>Sitecore uses three databases to maintain content. It always supports MS SQL server, but in Sitecore latest version 8.2 also supports <a href="https://kb.sitecore.net/articles/087164" target="_blank" rel="external">Oracle 12g</a>. But Oracle is only supported in <strong>CMS only mode, not for xDB</strong>.<br><img src="/css/images/oracle.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Sitecore CMS uses the following three databases,</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Core:</strong> This database contains all settings related to Sitecore, ex: Sitecore User Interface (Content Editor, Experience Editor, etc.) configuration. Using this database, we can add any new application, or shortcut on Sitecore launch pad or desktop.<br>This database also contains information about authentication and authorization, (Users &amp; roles)</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Master:</strong> This is content authoring database. All content authors mainly interact with this database, using either Content Editor or Experience Editor. It contains all versions of any content or assets.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Web:</strong> This is also called live database. It contains all the live content, which is serving on the production website. When content author modifies any content, and publish it, content copied over to web database. Master database contains all versions of content, whereas web database only contains live version of content. Web database is subset of the Master database.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When we log into Sitecore, by default it always displays content from Master database, but we can select the database to show the content from other databases, like as shown below,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/database-selection.png" alt=""></p>
<h5 id="Collection_Database__28Mongo_DB_29_3A"><a href="#Collection_Database__28Mongo_DB_29_3A" class="headerlink" title="Collection Database (Mongo DB):"></a>Collection Database (Mongo DB):</h5><p>As stated in Sitecore documentation, “In the Siteecore Experience Database (xDB), the <strong>Collection database</strong> is the central repository for storing contact, interaction, history &amp; automation data.”<br>It uses <strong>MongoDB</strong> - a highly scalable document-based NoSQL database solution.<br>Prior to Sitecore Version 7.5, all of analytics data used to get stored in <strong>Analytics</strong> database which was part of MS SQL server.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>tracking.live:</strong><br>The tracking.live database is used by two entities:</p>
<ol>
<li>Task Storage (defined in <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.config</em> file)</li>
<li>Live Processing Pool (defined in <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file)<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2508/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p><strong>tracking.history:</strong><br>The tracking.history database is used by only one entity:<br>History Processing Pool (defined in the <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file).<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2512/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>tracking.contact:</strong><br>The tracking.contact database is used by only one entity:<br>Contact Processing Pool (defined in the <em>Sitecore.Analytics.Processing.Aggregation.ProcessingPools.config</em> file).<br>read more information on <a href="http://sitecore.stackexchange.com/a/2525/1003" target="_blank" rel="external">Sitecore stackexchange</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="Reporting_Database_3A"><a href="#Reporting_Database_3A" class="headerlink" title="Reporting Database:"></a>Reporting Database:</h5><p>The reporting database is a SQL Server database that stores aggregated data from the collection database suitable for fast querying and reporting. This database contains aggregated data from collection DB.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;By this time, we have Sitecore website running in our machine, and also ready with Visual Studio solution setup. From now, we will look i
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Visual Studio - Project - Outside Web root</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Outside-webroot/</id>
    <published>2016-11-12T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.262Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent post we had seen, how to set up project inside the web root. But this option is only useful for POC’s. Most of the time outside web root option is more useful. In this post let’s explore more advanced,</p>
<p>I am using <strong>Visual Studio 2015 community/professional</strong> edition, and <strong>Sitecore 8.2</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Outside web root setup steps:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Open the Visual Studio, and navigate to <strong>File -&gt; New -&gt; Project</strong>, to create new project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Select the <strong>.NET Framework</strong> (in our case 4.5.2) version, and select the <strong>ASP.NET web application</strong> template.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enter the <strong>Name</strong> of the project, specify the <strong>Location</strong> field, and then click on OK to continue.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now we get another dialog, to select the project template. Here select <strong>Empty</strong> template present under <strong>ASP.NET 4.5.2 Templates</strong> section, and check the MVC checkbox as shown below, and click OK to proceed.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once the project is created, solution contains the files as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-solution-explorer.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now from the project, remove <strong>Web.config</strong>, and <strong>Global.asax</strong> files, otherwise while publishing, these files will override the respective Sitecore files.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-file-delete.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once after deleted, we need to copy both <strong>Web.config</strong> and <strong>Global.asax</strong> from web root into the project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-file-paste.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Create a folder with name <strong>App_Config</strong>, then copy the <strong>ConnectionStrings.config</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.config</strong> files from web root to the project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-config files.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-config files-copy.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Next step is to add Sitecore references. We need both <strong>Sitecore.Kernel.dll</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.MVC.dll</strong>, Let’s grab these files from web root. Create a directory in Project file system, let’s call that <strong>Assemblies</strong>, and copy the two dll’s to inside the directory.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-copy-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-copy-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-dll-reference.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Please double check on the Mvc version compatibility <a href="https://kb.sitecore.net/articles/087164" target="_blank" rel="external">here</a>, and make sure you are using correct .NET Mvc version. We can verify the MVC version in <strong>Web.config</strong> file as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-mvc-version.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now our project is all set. To deploy we need to create a publishing profile. Select <strong>Publishing Method</strong> as <strong>File System</strong> and specify the local Sitecore instance web root path.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-3.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>At last, click on the <strong>Publish</strong> button, we can see the Site is published to web root folder.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-profile-4.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>To confirm the publish to web root folder, we can navigate to bin folder in web root folder, and see that <strong>SIMSitecore.dll</strong> is copied over.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-publish-verification.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now try to load the site, and check whether we are able to login to Sitecore or not.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-deploy-verify-1.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-deploy-verify-2.png" alt=""></p>
<p>That’s all, thanks for reading.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;In recent post we had seen, how to set up project inside the web root. But this option is only useful for POC’s. Most of the time outside
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Visual Studio - Project - Inside Web root</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Inside-webroot/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/11/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore8.2-VS2015-Project-Inside-webroot/</id>
    <published>2016-11-05T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.227Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post we will look into creating Visual Studio project for the installed Sitecore.</p>
<p>There are mainly two approaches to create the project,</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Inside the web root</strong><br>Here both deployed files, and solution files in same location. Setting up is pretty straight forward, and good for small POC’s, but not recommended for real time projects.</li>
<li><strong>Outside the web root</strong><br>This is the most preferred one, as it separates the Sitecore, and our code and Sitecore in different locations, and easy to version Control. This is the <em>recommended</em> approach from core Sitecore team.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this post we will look into the first approach, I am using <strong>Visual Studio 2015</strong> edition.</p>
<p><strong>Inside the web root Setup steps:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Open the Visual Studio, and navigate to <strong>File -&gt; New -&gt; Project</strong>, to create new project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Select the <strong>.NET Framework</strong> (in our case 4.5.2) version, and select the <strong>ASP.NET web application</strong> template.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Enter the <strong>Name</strong> of the project, and in <strong>Location</strong> field specify the newly installed Sitecore web root path (in our case <em>F:\inetpub\wwwroot\SIMSitecore\Website</em>), and make sure to uncheck the <strong>Create directory for solution</strong> checkbox, and then click on OK button.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-new-project-name.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now we get another dialog, to select the project template. Here select <strong>Empty</strong> template present under <strong>ASP.NET 4.5.2 Templates</strong> section, and check the MVC checkbox as shown below, and click OK to proceed.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-MVC-project.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Once the project is created, solution contains the files/folders as shown below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-solution-explorer.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>If we go to the web root, we can observe there is a new folder created with the specified project name, and also new solution file (.sln) with the same name.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Drill down the newly created folder (SIMSitecore), to see the files, which are same as shown in the VS solution explorer.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/project-drilldown.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Close the VS solution. Copy the Properties directory, SIMSitecore.csproj, and SIMSitecore.csproj.user files to the main web root directory.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-inside-webroot-files.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li>Now delete the <strong><em>SIMSitecore subdirectory</em></strong>, which is present inside the Website directory.</li>
<li>Open the SIMSitecore.csproj file in Visual studio, and delete all the missing files from project.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/VS-remove-files.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Add references to <strong>Sitecore.Kernel.dll</strong> &amp; <strong>Sitecore.MVC.dll</strong> files which are in Website-&gt;bin directory.<br><img src="/css/images/VS-sitecore-kernerl.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Navigate to the Sitecore references</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>To be continued -having some trouble to setup</strong></p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;In this post we will look into creating Visual Studio project for the installed Sitecore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mainly two approaches to creat
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Launchpad</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Launchpad/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Launchpad/</id>
    <published>2016-10-29T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:20.958Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By this time, we have latest version (8.2) of Sitecore running in local. It’s ok to install using either of the three approaches, web application installer, or manual installation, or using SIM.</p>
<p>Before going ahead to create .NET web application, it’s good to have a look at Sitecore launch pad, different components, and the content tree structure.</p>
<p>For any application, to open Sitecore, we need to append <strong><em>/sitecore</em></strong> to the URL. In my case, URL is <a href="http://testsitecore/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://testsitecore/</a>, so to open Sitecore click on <a href="http://testsitecore/sitecore" target="_blank" rel="external">http://testsitecore/sitecore</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-login.png" alt=""></p>
<p>To login to Sitecore, default Administrator credentials are as below<br><strong><em>username: admin<br>password: b</em></strong></p>
<p>Once we login, we can see the Sitecore Launchpad,</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-latest-launchpad.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In the Launchpad, we can see there are 4 sections,</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong><em>Marketing Applications:</em></strong> This section contains, all the components relate to Digital Marketing suite. These are the main components using which marketers can connect better with customers.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Content Editing:</em></strong> This section is the main heart of the CMS. Using these components, Content Authors can add, edit, or delete the content.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Control Panel:</em></strong> As the name suggests, using these components, we can do the administrative activities, like Search indexing manager, clean up databases, and localization.. etc.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong><em>Access Management:</em></strong> This section contains all the user, role, and security related components.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Now we look into some of the main components,</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Content Editor:</em></strong> This is where Content Authors manage content. They can either add, edit, or delete the content. As a <em>developer</em>, we frequently access this to create templates, rendering, and placeholders etc. In this all items are displayed in tree structure.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-content-editor.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Experience Editor:</em></strong> Here Content Authors can create/modify the content in the live mode. In previous Sitecore versions this was called Page Editor.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-experience-editor.png" alt=""></p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Experience Analytics:</em></strong> This section contains more of reports, like Channel groups by visits, Top campaigns by value, Top goals by conversions, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-experience-analytics.png" alt=""></p>
<p>In the next post, we will look into how to create a .NET web project for Sitecore.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;By this time, we have latest version (8.2) of Sitecore running in local. It’s ok to install using either of the three approaches, web app
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Installation with SIM tool</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Sitecore-Installation-Using-SIM/</id>
    <published>2016-10-22T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.193Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: Sitecore with SIM"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: Sitecore with SIM</h3><p>Last week, we had seen how to install Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM) tool. This week we will explore how to install Sitecore using SIM.</p>
<p>Among all the three (<strong>Web Application Installer, Manual Installation, and SIM</strong>) available options, to choose, SIM is the most preferred choice among all the Sitecore developers. The Main reason for that is the flexibility it provides in managing the Sitecore sites.</p>
<p>Let’s dive into step by step Sitecore installation,</p>
<p><strong>Step 1:</strong><br>If we remember in the last post, while installing SIM, we configured <em>4 settings</em>, these are very crucial while installing Sitecore. Before proceeding any further, we need to double check on these settings, and if it is required, make any necessary changes.</p>
<ul>
<li>Instance Root Folder</li>
<li>SQL Server Connection String</li>
<li>Sitecore License File</li>
<li>Local repository (Make sure to place downloaded Sitecore zip folder inside this path)</li>
</ul>
<p>To verify the 4 options, open the Home tab, and click on the Settings</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-home.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 2:</strong><br>For additional settings, click on Advanced Settings. But before making any changes, please go through the <a href="https://github.com/sitecore/sitecore-instance-manager/wiki/Advanced" target="_blank" rel="external">documentation</a> very carefully.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-advanced-settings.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 3:</strong><br>Click on the Install Instance<br><img src="/css/images/SIM-install-instance.png" alt=""></p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-install-new-instance.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 4:</strong><br>Make all the necessary changes, Site Name, and Host name. Location value is prepopulated from the settings <em>Instance Root Folder</em>. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-new-sitecore.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 5:</strong><br>Some more options for instance details. Better to keep the default values, until and unless you are fully aware of the modifications. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-instance-details.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 6:</strong><br>If any of the Sitecore modules are present in the <em>Instance Root Folder</em>, those all are going to be listed here. We can select the modules, to install with Sitecore. Click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-module-list.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 7:</strong><br>You can select any available custom packages, and click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-custom-packages.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 8:</strong><br>Select any Configuration presets, and click on <em>Next</em> to proceed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-configuration-presets.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 9:</strong><br>Finally all the selected modules, and custom packages, will be listed for review. Make any final modification and click on <em>Install</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-instance-review.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 10:</strong><br>Now Sitecore is getting installed.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-sitecore-installation.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 11:</strong><br>Once the installation is completed, you can check the listed options, and click on <em>Finish</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/SIM-sitecore-installation-finish.png" alt=""></p>
<p>See you on next <strong><em>Saturday</em></strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Sitecore_with_SIM&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM) </title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-SIM-Installation/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-SIM-Installation/</id>
    <published>2016-10-15T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.078Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: SIM tool Installation"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: SIM tool Installation</h3><p>Sitecore Instance Manager (SIM), is the tool, using which we can install, maintain, and uninstall the Sitecore. Among Sitecore developers, this is the most preferred choice to maintain Sitecore installations.</p>
<p>SIM provides rich set of choices, you can watch this wonderful <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bqYhjoW83RE" target="_blank" rel="external">video</a>, in which <a href="https://twitter.com/vasiliyfomichev" target="_blank" rel="external">Vasiliy Fomichev</a> explains the main features.</p>
<p>In this post, we will look into SIM installation, in the next we will look into Sitecore installation using SIM.</p>
<p>Installation Steps</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Download SIM tool from [Sitecore Marketplace] (<a href="https://marketplace.sitecore.net/en/Modules/Sitecore_Instance_Manager.aspx" target="_blank" rel="external">https://marketplace.sitecore.net/en/Modules/Sitecore_Instance_Manager.aspx</a>).<br><img src="/css/images/SIM1.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on the <strong>Link</strong> to get the ClickOnce version of SIM.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM2.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>It will be redirected to <a href="http://dl.sitecore.net/updater/sim/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://dl.sitecore.net/updater/sim/</a>. From here click on <strong>Install and Launch</strong>.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM3.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on the downloaded <strong>SIM.Tool.application</strong><br><img src="/css/images/SIM4.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>On the Initial Configuration Wizard, click on Next to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM5.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Click on Next to proceed.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM6.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>In the previous post, we had downloaded latest Sitecore Zip (<strong>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729</strong>) file. For local repository point to the location of Sitecore folder, and point the local path for Sitecore License file.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM7.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Here give a SQL connection string, with <strong>(Data Source, User ID and Password)</strong> values.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM8.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>Specify the File system path, and make sure to give the Network Service access, by clicking on the <strong>Grant</strong> button.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM9.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM10.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/SIM11.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
<li><p>After the successful installation, SIM will check for any sitecore websites in the specified File System path. In my local I already have TestSitecore website, the same is listed below.<br><img src="/css/images/SIM12.png" alt=""></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_SIM_tool_Installation&quot; class=&quot;headerlin
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday Sitecore Learning - Manual Installation</title>
    <link href="http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Manual-Installation/"/>
    <id>http://gopigujjula.com/2016/10/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning-Manual-Installation/</id>
    <published>2016-10-08T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-26T11:03:21.018Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File"><a href="#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File" class="headerlink" title="Saturday Sitecore Learning: Manual Installation: Installing from the .ZIP File"></a>Saturday Sitecore Learning: Manual Installation: Installing from the .ZIP File</h3><p>In this post, we will look into Manual installation option.</p>
<p><strong><em>Installation Overview:</em></strong><br>Before proceeding, we need to understand what will happen in the installation process. In my previous post we discussed about installation using executable(.exe). There after giving all the information, and click on the install button, in the background it will perform the below operations,</p>
<ul>
<li>Creates 5 databases, like shown below,<br><img src="/css/images/sitecoredb.png" alt=""></li>
<li>Copies Sitecore site in the specified destination folder path.</li>
<li>Creates new website in IIS, and point to the destination folder.</li>
<li>Takes care of the other details like updating the database information in <em>ConnectionStrings.config</em> file, folder securities, and other configurations.</li>
</ul>
<p>When we go through manual installation, we need to take care of all the above steps.</p>
<p><strong><em>Sitecore Manual Installation:</em></strong><br>I have downloaded latest Sitecore .ZIP file (<em>Sitecore 8.2 rev. 160729</em>) from <a href="https://dev.sitecore.net/" target="_blank" rel="external">dev.sitecore.net</a>. Unzip the file, then we can see the three folders as shown below, copy all these three folders to destination folder.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/sitecore-folders.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now we will look into Database setup,</p>
<p><strong>Step 1</strong>: Open SQL Server Management Studio (SSMS) in Admin mode, Right click on Databases, and select Attach new databases. All the .mdf and .ldf files are present inside the Databases folder, which can be found in the unzipped folder. Attach all five databases.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/attach-db.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 2</strong>: Next step is to create new user. Navigate to Security –&gt;Login, and click on ‘New Login’, and map all the five databases, <em>with db_owner role</em>.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/db-login.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1a.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1b.png" alt=""><br><img src="/css/images/new-login-1c.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now all the databases are set.</p>
<p>Next we will proceed to Website setup:</p>
<p><strong>Step 1</strong>: Copy your Sitecore license (<em>license.xml</em>) file under Data folder, and update the path in <em>Website\App_Config\Sitecore.config</em> file.<br><figure class="highlight plain"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">&#60;sc.variable name=&#34;dataFolder&#34; value=&#34;F:\inetpub\wwwroot\Data&#34; /&#62;</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure></p>
<p><strong>Step 2</strong>: Update the <em>ConnectionStrings.config</em> file, which is present in <em>Website\App_Config</em> path.<br><img src="/css/images/connectionstring.png" alt=""></p>
<p><strong>Step 3:</strong> Open IIS, and create new website, and make sure to add new host with site name.</p>
<p><img src="/css/images/IIS-website.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Now run the site, it will load the Sitecore default home page.<br>In next post we will explore the Sitecore installation option using SIM.</p>
<p><strong>Happy Learning :)</strong></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;h3 id=&quot;Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_Installation_3A_Installing_from_the_-ZIP_File&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Saturday_Sitecore_Learning_3A_Manual_I
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/categories/Sitecore/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Beginner" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Beginner/"/>
    
      <category term="Saturday Sitecore Learning" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Saturday-Sitecore-Learning/"/>
    
      <category term="Sitecore" scheme="http://gopigujjula.com/tags/Sitecore/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
